<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two treatises. 1. The holy exercise  of a true fast, described out of God's word. / Written by T.C. ; 2. The substance of the Lordes Supper. / Written by T.W..</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 102 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07431</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S91274</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">71305120</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 71305120</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183865</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07431)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183865)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2205:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two treatises. 1. The holy exercise  of a true fast, described out of God's word. / Written by T.C. ; 2. The substance of the Lordes Supper. / Written by T.W..</title>
                  <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1535-1603.</author>
                  <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 99, [11], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for I. Harison, and T. Man.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1610..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within border of printer's ornaments; initials.</note>
                  <note>STC (2nd ed.) attributes part 1 to T. Cartwright, and part 2 to T. Wilcox.</note>
                  <note>"The substance of the Lordes Supper" has special t.p. and separate paging; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H¹² I⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, faded, stained, and tightly bound, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology, Practical --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fasting --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:183865:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:183865:1"/>
                  <p>TWO Treatiſes. </p>
                  <p>1. The holy exerciſe of a true Faſt, deſcribed out of Gods word, Written by T. C.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Joel.</hi> 2.12.13.</bibl>
                     <p>Turne you vnto me (ſaith the Lord) with all your heart, and with faſting, and with weeping, and with mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: And rent your heart and not your clothes; and turne vnto the Lord your God, for he it gracious, and mercifull ſlow to anger, and of great kindneſſe, and repenteth him of the euill.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>2. The ſubſtance of the Lordes Supper. Written by T. W.</p>
                  <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>I. Hariſon,</hi> and <hi>T. Man. Anno.</hi> 1610.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb facs="tcp:183865:2"/>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="1" facs="tcp:183865:2"/>
                     <head>THE HOLY EXERCISE OF a true Faſt, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed out of Gods word.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T IS AN euident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, of a marueilous blindneſſe which is in vs, to order our ſteppes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the kingdome of heauen; that like children new come into the world, we know not when to eate, and when to forbeare ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, no further then wee haue our direction out of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:183865:3"/> Gods word: But it is yet more maruaile, that in ſo ſmall a matter, ſcarſe the hundred perſon, of thoſe which profeſſe the name of Chriſt, know either how to enter into this way, or how to turne them in it when they are entred, to any glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of GOD, or profite of them ſelves. For to let the Papiſts goe, which through a ſhamefull ſuperſtition in it, rather pine away their ſoules, then take downe their bodies: it is a ſhame to ſpeake, how few there are of thoſe which beare the name of Goſpellers, that haue ſo much as the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this exerciſe; ſo farre are they from any lawfull and right practiſe of it. For a great number,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:183865:3"/> as a needleſſe thing, reiect it altogeather; For ſhaking off the Popiſh yoke, from their owne necks, by vſing, or rather abuſing their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie; they ſuffer their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to remaine ſtill vnder it. Which cuſtome, vnleſſe it be through infirmitie of body, or ſome other weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie cauſe; it can hardly eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the hotte and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuſpition, either of belly-Gods, if thinking it religious in their ſeruantes, they them-ſelues will not obſerue it: or of a couetous minde, if hauing no ſuch opinion of it, they doe notwithſtanding conſtraine their ſeruantes therevnto. An other ſort there bee, which being afraide of the reproche of Belly-gods,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:183865:4"/> and thinking it fitting to the Chriſtian profeſsion, to keepe the fleſh in ſome bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; allow (in deede) of the exerciſe of Faſting; but for want of knowledge of a better, they ſticke ſtill in the mire of the Popiſh faſt. For remedie whereof, there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth a Treatiſe, whereby the true Faſt being vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded; as well the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane opinion of thoſe which reiect this exerciſe, as the fooliſh ſuperſtition of thoſe, which content them ſelues with a ſhadow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is laid open.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Faſting therfore, is an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence commanded of the Lord, thereby to make ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne profeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</q> Wherein, that which is ſayd of the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:183865:4"/> it, is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered againſt thoſe, which would thruſt this exerciſe, out of the doores of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Churches. For the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing of which errour, let that be called to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, which the Lord commanded by <hi>Moſes:</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Leuit 16.29, 30, 31, &amp; 23.27 to 33 Num. 29.7.</note> That euery ſoule once a yeare ſhould humble it ſelfe, in faſting before the Lord, in one of the great aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of his people. For although the ceremonie of the day be taken away by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of our Sauiour Chriſt; yet the thing it ſelfe is no more taken away, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a reſt for Gods ſeruice is ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, becauſe the <hi>Iewes</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both is aboliſhed. For, when as (no doubt) the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Faſt was,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:183865:5"/> that the wrath of GOD ſhould not breake out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; or being bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out, ſhould be cauſed to returne home againe: the ſame cauſe remaining, there is good reaſon the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſhould continue. And when it is an humbling of a man before his God; was there any degree of caſting downe, neceſſarie for that people, which is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for vs? Either ought they to haue gone downe lower into the conceite of their vnworthineſſe, then we, into the conſcience of our guiltineſſe; Whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, as they are greater then theirs; ſo the abuſe of them, ſhould driue vs to the loweſt humiliation that can be; ſo it be lawfull &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:183865:5"/> by the word of God.</p>
                     <p>But if this holy exerciſe of Faſting, doe not clearely enough appeare, to be no fading or ſhadowing cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, by this ſet and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Faſt, becauſe the like doth not agree with the time of the Goſpell: yet by other moueable and vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Faſtes, which were holden vpon occaſion, the ſame may bee more ſtrongly ſtrengthened. For where we ſee the like occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of faſt, that was then; there we may be aſſured of the ſame commaundement to faſt, that was giuen them: commaundement I ſay, leaſt any man thinking it to be a will worſhip, taken vp at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:183865:6"/> the pleaſure of men, might thinke he had as good (or better) right to lay it downe, then they had, to take it vp. For proofe whereof, that one place of the Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> ſhall ſuffice;<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.22.</note> which, vpon occaſion of a great dearth in the Land, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth in the Lords be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, to ſanctifie a Faſt. By which one commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is euident, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Faſtes, which were kept, either by the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches publiquely, or by ſome of the faythfull pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatly; were done in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and not at the randon of mans inuention. If this be not ſufficient, to ſubdue our ſturdie affections, to this ſo holy an exerciſe; yet at the leaſt, let them ſtoupe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:183865:6"/> vnder ſo manifeſt, both doctrine &amp; examples here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by the Churches of God vnderneath the Goſpell. For when as our Sauiour Chriſt, being charged by the <hi>Phariſes</hi> and <hi>Iohns</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,<note place="margin">Luke. 5.33.</note> that his Diſciples fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted not; ſo anſwered, that he did not onely not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne it, but highly alſo commend it; ſo it were done ſeaſonably: It is plaine, that the libertie which the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell bringeth, hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued the auncient bound of a Chriſtian Faſt. And if we looke into the practiſe, whereby the way chalked out by his doctrine, is tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and beaten plaine vnto vs by examples; it will ſoone be ſeene, how great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they deceiue them ſelues,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:183865:7"/> which vnder the colour of greater perfection attained vnder the Goſpell, caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the aſsiſtance, that the Lord offereth by this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe. For if we enquire of the Churches &amp; Apoſtles faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then was it moſt often, when they were fulleſt of the graces of God: that is, after the ſolemne ſending of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                     <p>If wee thinke then, that this exerciſe of faſt, be too ceremonious, becauſe it was tied to a certaine day: the commaundement to hold it without any ſuch reſtraint, vnto a certaine time, ought to correct that thought of ours. If we ſtand in feare, that it ſhould be too Iewiſh; the doctrine of the Goſpell is ready to pull vs out of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:183865:7"/> that feare. If preſumption of greater graces, then thoſe which ſhould neede ſuch a ſupplie, doe bring this Faſt out of conceit with vs: the practiſe of it by the holy Apoſtles, at the higheſt toppe of their perfection in this world, will eaſily ſet vp the credite thereof againe. But if Faſtes, neither ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding nor ſitting, neither vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, nor vnder the Goſpell, neither of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, nor of the ſtronger, can draw vs into loue, and (in loue) into practiſe thereof; it muſt needs be confeſſed, that there is a maruellous poiſon of rebellion in our natures, which all this tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acle of the Lords high au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and of ſuch autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized examples of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:183865:9"/> of God, will not caſt foorth. Howbeit, the Lord leaueth vs not here, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Lordly authoritie, of commaunding this exerciſe of Faſt, hath added fatherly promiſes, to allure vs vnto the ſame: as towardes the end of this Treatiſe, ſhall plainely appeare.</p>
                     <p>This exerciſe therfore of Faſting, being both of ſuch authoritie, and of ſo great weight to pull wrath vpon vs, if it be neglected; let vs now ſee in what things (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially) it doth conſiſt. And they are in number two. The former is of the outward, and (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calleth it,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note>) of the bodily exerciſe: the other is of the inward vertues, helped for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by the bodily exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:183865:9"/> For the outward cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, it is an abſtinence for a time, from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities and pleaſures of this life, thereby to make vs the apter to the inward ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. <q>And this outward ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence is therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, that wee ſhould both feele, and in feeling, profeſſe that we are vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy either of life, or of any thing that belongeth to the vpholding thereof.</q> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, it may appeare but a childiſh thing to carnall men, and a thing vnworthy the wiſedom of the Goſpel, to place any thing in this bodily exerciſe, ſeeing that the Lord is a Spirit, &amp; will be worſhipped in ſpirit &amp; trueth; and ſeeing that they being of their owne nature,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:183865:8"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:183865:8"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:183865:10"/> neither good nor euill, can not make vs either better or worſe: yet if wee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that it is the Lordes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, who hath ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded it, we can not be but moſt aſſured, that the Lord who hath ſo inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, will giue it a bleſsing, and cauſe it to proſper, to that end whervnto he hath ordeined it; if wee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take it in his feare, and in a conſcience of obeying the Lordes commaundement. Thoſe which came either to runne,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.25.</note> or to wraſtle for the beſt Game, were wont to abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch things as might hinder their exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, or make them leſſe able to performe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with praiſe: And whatſoeuer, either pith in their armes, or ſwiftneſſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:183865:10"/> in their legges, they had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; yet as they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected not that abſtinence, ſo they found that it greatly profited them, to the better breathing and other inhab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of them, to their exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes. And ſhall we thinke, that the dyet which the Lord him ſelfe hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, to the fitting of vs towardes the ſpirituall wraſtling with our fleſhly minde, ſhall not haue a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular fruite? And if there were no other fruite of this Abſtinence, but that the enimies mouth ſhould thus be ſtopped, which charge the Goſpell, to ſet open a ſchoole to all licentiouſnes of eating, and to giue (as it were) a ſauce to prouoke mens appetites therevnto,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:183865:11"/> which are otherwiſe too ſharpe ſet of them ſelues: it ſhould be no ſmall effect of our Abſtinence. In deed the Papiſtes charge vpon vs, is heere the ſame and no other,<note place="margin">Luke. 5 33.</note> then the Phariſes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Diſciples of our Sauiour Chriſt: But why ſhould not we, if we deſire that the Goſpell ſhould be well ſpoken of, take away the occaſion of ſuch ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches?</p>
                     <p>But let vs ſee wherein this Abſtinence doth conſiſt; where firſt of all commeth to be conſidered, the Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from Meates and Drinkes; whereof (as the principall of the outward Obſeruations) the whole exerciſe tooke the name.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.16.17. Ezr. 10.6. Leui 23.32. Iudg. 20.26</note> 
                        <q>And the word it ſelfe with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:183865:11"/> the practiſe, declare, that it is not onely a ſober vſe of Meates, which ought to be continuall all the life long, or a more ſparing diet then at other times: but an vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Abſtinence from eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to euening, from all kind of meates &amp; drinkes.</q> Whereby it appeareth, that the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Faſt is nothing leſſe, then the Faſt which the Scripture teacheth: for they breake the necke of this Abſtinence both by fulneſſe and by delicacie. By fulneſſe, in that it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (as other dayes) at Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to fill them ſelues with anything, fleſh only excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: at euening &amp; morning, to fill the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues with Bread and Drinke. By delicacie for that, where men on that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:183865:12"/> day, ſhould content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with common and courſe meats, ſufficient one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of health: the <hi>Papiſtes</hi> in their abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, did either not ſo much as aime at this marke, or elſe they ſhotte groſſely wide. For in permitting the vſe of all thinges at their Dinner, beſides Fleſh; it is euident, that they left grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dainties, &amp; greater ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of fleſhly luſtes, then they did cut off. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the dainties in meates; Wine, (then which there is nothing more prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king) was as vſuall that day, as of others. And at euening, when they would giue the cleareſt teſtimonie of their Abſtinence, and when they did light their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:183865:12"/> candles (as it were to ſhew their abſtinence by; the greateſt part of thoſe that were both able and might finde in their heartes, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it of them ſelues, had their Tables furniſhed with Spice-bread, with Fruites of this ſide and beyonde the Seas, with Marmelet and Sucket, and ſuch like: then which dealing, what could be more childiſh? to deny the taſting onely of one morſell of Fleſh, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a fulneſſe of bread: to forbid the courſer Meates and Table, which might haue bin furniſhed for two pence, and to draw in the delicateſt Meates, which could not be prouided for twentie ſhillinges: to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine the vſe of thinges
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:183865:13"/> bredde at home, and to leaue the vſe free, of thinges fetched out of <hi>Barbarie:</hi> finally to condemne the eating of a peece of ſmoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie and reaſtie Bakon, and to iuſtifie the banqueting and iunqueting Diſhes, which are before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. That I ſpeake nothing of ſome of the poorer ſort, which vpon the Thurſday at night, and Fryday at din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, would fill their bellies the fuller, that they might paſſe ouer their abſtinence, with leſſe feeling the want of their accuſtomed diet. All which thinges, as wee condmne in the <hi>Papiſtes;</hi> ſo we muſt carefully take heed that they be not found in vs:<note place="margin">Rom. 2.1.</note> vnleſſe we haue forgot, that in iudging them, wee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:183865:13"/> condemne our ſelues, when as we doe the ſame thinges, which we finde fault woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>An other of theſe corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall exerciſes is watching, or a cutting ſhort of our ordinarie ſleepe: which we may apply to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of this exerciſe.</q> For beſide that this Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, is a remouing of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie pleaſures and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities; it appeareth, that ſome thing alſo ſhould be pared from it. For beſide that, it is meete that there ſhould be a certaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie and ſutableneſſe of our whole behauiour, all the time of the Faſt. The Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> exhorting the Prieſtes to this holy exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Faſt,<note place="margin">Ioel. 1.13.</note> biddeth them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:183865:14"/> that they ſhould continue in Sackcloth in the night time, extending this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe (at the leaſt) to ſome part of the night. When notwithſtanding it is to be noted, that as wel in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer abſtinence from meate as in this withdrawing of ſome part of ſleepe; that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſo ſtreightly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Lord, but that thoſe whoſe either diſeaſe or other infirmitie will not beare this abſtinence, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hazard of their health may vſe ſo much libertie, as ſhall ſerue for the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their health: ſo they take heed they vſe not this gentle dealing of the Lord, as a cloake to hide the luſtes of their fleſh withall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <q>A third kind of abſtinence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:183865:14"/> is in the apparel, that albeit they put not on Sackcloth and Aſhes, as the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did in times paſt; yet that they content the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues with a common kind of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, auoyding all ſuch coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe &amp; curioſitie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in tricking &amp; trimming vp them ſelues,, the fleſh may take occaſion of being proud.</q> Thus the Lord, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he would haue the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to humble them ſelues before him, ſpake to <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaying;<note place="margin">Exod. 33.5.</note> Speake vnto the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that for the preſent time, they lay aſide their Iewels and Ornamentes, that I may know what I ſhall doe with them. And thus farre hath it been ſpoken of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Exerciſes, which are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:183865:15"/> generall, and to be done of al, which make this ſolemne profeſsion of repentaunce. There is one yet which is more ſpeciall, belonging vnto married perſons alone, which is, that they for the time,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.5.</note> ſhould with conſent <q>abſtaine from the mutuall felowſhip one of an other; which is ſo ſtraitly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.16.</note> that euen the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome &amp; the Bride, (which of all other, ought to haue the greateſt priuiledge in that poynt) are bidden at ſuch times, to come out of their chambers.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 14.17.</note>But for as much, as the kingdome of heauen ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not in theſe thinges; and the Lord being a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, will be worſhipped in ſpirite and trueth: either
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:183865:15"/> theſe exerciſes muſt lead vs to ſome farther thing, or elſe the ſame accuſation will lie againſt vs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Prophet charged the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them ſelues with the outward ceremonie of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence,<note place="margin">Eſay. 58.3.</note> were ſent home as emptie as they came. And indeed, vnleſſe we bring more with vs, then this our abſtinencie, our Faſtes may be matched with the Beaſts Faſt of <hi>Niniuie;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ionas. 3.7.</note> for they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo both eate nothing, and were couered with Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth: yea the Beaſtes Faſt, may be ſo much better then ours, as there be ſome kinds of Beaſtes, that can longer endure without meate and ſleepe then we. Where the <hi>Papiſtes</hi> faſt, which was ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:183865:16"/> before to be childiſh, may heere be prooued to be beaſtly and brutiſh: For if they did onely abſtaine from Meate, they iudged them ſelues to haue holden a good Faſt vnto the Lord. There follow the inwarde vertues helped forward by the bodily exerciſe; which in the number<note n="*" place="margin">Ezdra. 6.21.</note> two. <q>The one is the humbling and caſting downe of our ſelues before the high Maieſtie of God, with ſorrow for our ſinnes: The other, is the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuraunce that we haue, that with forgiueneſſe of them, we ſhall obtaine the thing that we ſtande in need of, and make ſuite for.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here therefore, firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be conſidered, our hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling &amp; caſting downe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:183865:16"/> which is a vile eſteeming of our ſelues, anſwering to the outward exerciſe. <q>For ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe we abſtaine for a time, that we might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by haue a quicker feeling of our owne vnworthines. Therefore we bring downe the body, that the minde may be likewiſe brought downe.</q> Therefore we cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the fleſh, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued death of the ſpirite, may be the better knowen. <q>Therfore we abſtaine from our pleaſures and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities,<note place="margin">Mark. 2.20. Luk. 5.35. Math. 9.15.</note> that through conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſinne, and feeling of the wrath of God, either preſent, or to come, for the ſame, we might draw our ſelues to a greater ſorrow.</q> In which reſpect, the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe which the other Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſtes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:183865:17"/> call Faſting, Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> calleth Mourning. <q>Herevpon it commeth,<note place="margin">Ioel. 2 17. 1. Sam. 7.6.</note> that weeping, which is a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our ſorrow, is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed vnto the Faſt;</q> which the children of God haue done ſo plentifully in this exerciſe,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 7.6.</note> that they haue bin ſayd, to haue drawne whole Buckets of Water; which the deapth of the ſorrow for their ſinnes, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of God againſt them hath miniſtred. And as theſe outward exerciſes are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, to draw vs to a feeling of our vnworthines; ſo in the feeling thereof, by them wee make a ſolemne confeſsion of the ſame. <q>For the children of God in time paſt, by their abſtinence from meate &amp; drinke, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:183865:17"/> them ſelues vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſo much as of a crumme of bread, or drop of water: by putting on Sackcloth, vnworthy of the worſt rag to couer their ſhame with. So that if common honeſtie and health would haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, they wold haue ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped them ſelues ſtarke na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. The ſame is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded of the benefite of Sleepe, and company of Mariage; as alſo of all other the commodities of this life: whereof they did not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſe them ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, but in that they put Duſt and Aſhes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their heades, they gaue to vnderſtande, that they were vnworthie of the life it ſelfe, and that they deſerued to bee as farre
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:183865:18"/> vnderneath the ground, as they were aboue it: yea if there had been any thing, apter to haue ſet forth their euerlaſting condemnation in Hell, of that alſo would they haue borne the marke, thereby to declare their guilt &amp; deſert of the ſame. So that hereby they do iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the Lord, in that ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by this humbling of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, they ſeeke redreſſe.</q> If then we keepe a holy Faſt vnto the Lord, wee muſt thereby be humbled in our ſelues before the Lord: but if vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confidence of our faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Luk. 5.33. Luk. 18.11.</note> wee waxe bolder to ſinne, in a perſwaſion that through obedience giuen vnto him, in this one poynt, we may be bolder to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:183865:18"/> in others: or if the vſe hereof do make vs ſwell againſt our brethren, and after the example of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> deſpiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which doe not Faſt, as wee doe: then is the Faſt, appoynted of the Lord for our medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, become our bane and poyſon.</p>
                     <p>And therefore here now, we giue a new charge vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Popiſh Faſt, a great deale more hotte then the former: For ſeeing that they with the proude <hi>Phariſee,</hi> boaſt of the merite of their faſtes, ſetting theſe faſtes (as other workes) in the place of the Blood of Chriſt. It is manifeſt, that their Faſtes are ſo farre from humbling them, that through the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of them, they riſe vp
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:183865:19"/> againſt the Lord, and doe their beſt to ſet them ſelues, euen in the throne of God: ſo that vnto the childiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and brutiſhneſſe of their Faſt abouementioned, heere they haue added an horrible and blaſphemous ſacriledge. <q>To the compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of this true humbling of our ſinnes, is annexed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, an information and meditation of the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our ſinnes, and of the iuſt vengeance of the Lord againſt them, declared in the threatninges of the Law, and execution of the iudgements of God againſt the wicked; and namely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Sauiour Chriſt, who putting vpon himſelfe our wickedneſſe, ſuffered Hell paines for it: and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:183865:19"/> an information and meditation of thoſe, both ſinnes and puniſhmentes, which the preſent time and perſons doe giue occaſion of.</q> And thus farre touching the firſt part of the inwarde vertues in Faſting, ſtanding in the caſting downe of our ſelues before the Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>There followeth the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part, which is a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Fayth, that wee ſhall be lifted vp as high, through the grace of the Lord our God in Ieſus Chriſt, as the conſcience of our ſinnes doth caſt vs downe:</q> and that wee ſhall obtaine the remoouing of the euilles tending to our deſtruction, (through the woorthineſſe of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt,) which either
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:183865:20"/> preſently preſſe vs, or hang ouer our heads, through our owne vnworthineſſe. For as true repentance, caſting vs downe with one hand, both in ſorrowe for our ſinnes, &amp; confeſsion of the ſame, leaueth vs not in our downfal, but through faith, reacheth vs the other hand, to lift vs vp againe: ſo this ſolemne profeſsion of our repentance, carying vs firſt to the valley of trouble, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward bringeth vs backe againe, to the gate of hope. In which reſpect, wee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes finde in the holy Scriptures,<note n="*" place="margin">Ezra. 9.5. Nehe. 1.4. Dan. 9 3. Iudg. 20.26. Luk. 5.33. 1. Cor. 7.7.</note> that Faſting is ioyned with praier;<note n="*" place="margin">2. Chron. 20.6. Iames. 1.6. Iohn. 16.23</note> which can neuer be truly made, without hope of obtaining the grace, that is praied for. But for as much as prayer is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:183865:20"/> a dayly and ordinarie exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Gods children; it is manifeſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Ionas. 3.8. Eſay. 58.4.</note> that by the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which is coupled with Faſting, there is vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a ſpeciall or peereleſſe kinde of Prayer, both in zeale and ſtrength of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as alſo in continuance of the ſame. <q>Whereby appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that here is an other vſe of the outwarde abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, that it might be as it were a wing, wherewith the Prayer, that otherwiſe through earthly affections, creepeth vpon the ground, might the eaſier flee vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen: and that it might be a Grindeſtone, to make a poynt of it, that it may pierce; and to ſet an edge, that it may cut, both the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and inuiſible enimies,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:183865:21"/> which wee pray againſt. And therefore the outward abſtinence that pulleth downe the body, helpeth to lift vp the minde; and cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the fleſh, it quickneth the ſpirite, and maketh it more liuely to this exerciſe.</q> Where yet againe the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Faſt is founde inſufficient, which vpon the dayes of their Faſtes, had no extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie exerciſes of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; more then other dayes which were not faſted. <q>To the better performance al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of this part, is annexed an information and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the gracious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God, eſpecially ſuch as may ſerue for reliefe of the preſent occaſions.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Wherein the better to correct our dulneſſe &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:183865:21"/> to this ſo holy an exerciſe; let vs remember, that it is to obtaine ſome ſpeciall grace at the hand of the Lord. Whereby it is giuen vs to vnderſtand, that vpon due holding of this Faſt vnto the Lord, there be excellent promiſes, and a moſt ſingular rewarde.<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.13. &amp; 19.20.</note> Whereof the place of <hi>Ioel,</hi> as it ſpake before, for the commaundement of all the Faſtes, which the people of God vſed; ſo will it vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take for the promiſes, which the Lord hath made, to all thoſe which ſubmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to the obedience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. The truth of which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes is ſo manifeſt in the Scriptures; as the Sunne (at noone dayes) can be no clearer. For let all the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:183865:22"/> Faſtes of the holy Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and of godly men layd out in Scripture, both of the old and new Teſtament, be<note n="*" place="margin">Iudg 20.23. Ezra. 19.6. Heſt. 4.16. 2. Chron. 20.3.</note> turned ouer; and it ſhall be ſeene, that the ende of their Faſt (which kept it in any meaſure of trueth and ſimplicitie) was a Feaſt, and the iſſue of their mourning, great reioycing.<note place="margin">Dan. 9.20. Ionah. 2.10.</note> For albeit the ordinarie Prayers of the faithfull, returne not empty vnto them againe; yet ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing regarde vnto theſe, which are ioyned with this Exerciſe,<note place="margin">Act. 12.5. Act. 13.2.</note> they may worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeme to be barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which are otherwiſe fruitfull; and to be blaſted, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſeeme full cared. Yea, the Faſt of the wicked king <hi>Achab,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 21.27.</note> ioyned with no true repentaunce, nor ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:183865:22"/> much as with any true knowledge how to ſerue the Lord, but performed in ſome ſort onely in keeping of the outward and bodily ceremonie, went not vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded from the Lord. For euen by the very ſhadow of his exerciſe, the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that iudgment, which was awarded againſt him, touching his vtter raſing from the kingdome of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el:</hi> was deferred vntill his ſonnes dayes. Now, if the comming within the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of this exerciſe, doth heale ſome diſeaſes: what will it doe if wee come to touch the body thereof? And if the leaues of it, haue ſome vertue to preſerue men from the vengeance of God; how ſoueraigne is the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:183865:23"/> fruite, to deliuer vs from the wrath to come? And if the ordinarie obedience of the children of God, goeth not emptie, and vnrewarded from the preſence of God: this extraordinarie obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence &amp; exerciſe in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe of God, muſt needes receiue ſpeciall, and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie bleſsinges from his hand.<note place="margin">1. Regum 20.29.</note> When <hi>Benhadab</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> King, ouercome by <hi>Achab</hi> king of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was out of hope of any ſafety; at the length, by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of his ſeruantes, he put him ſelfe and his company in Sackcloth,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 20.31. to 35.</note> with Ropes about their neckes; think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by humbling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues before the King, to obtaine pardon: which came to paſſe accordingly.</p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:183865:23"/>
                     <p>If therefore, men in hope of obtaining pardon, will humble themſelues to them of whom they haue no promiſe, that they ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine any thing: how much more ought wee to doe it, which haue ſo ſure Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of good ſucceſſe? And if mercie was obtained of men, in whom there is ſcant a droppe of that pittie and compaſsion, which is ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the Lord; we may be well aſſured, that wee ſhall not miſſe of it at his hand. And if one enimie, can looke for it at the hand of an other; wee may with greater aſſuraunce, looke for it at the hande of the Lord; to whom we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie reconciled, by the blood of his Sonne.</p>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:183865:24"/>
                     <p>Therefore, if the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Lord ſhould not compell vs; yet the moſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall and certaine promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſhould allure vs to this exerciſe. <q>Which if wee doe not, what remayneth, but that ſuch as will not Faſt, with the children of God, muſt eate and drinke of the furious wrath of God, with the wicked: they that will not weepe with the one, muſt howle with the other.</q> And finally, they that will haue no part in the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment giuen hereof, to both the peoples, vnder the Law and vnder the Goſpel; muſt haue no part in the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes made to any of them: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the Lord threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth;<note place="margin">Leui. 23.29. Luk. 5, 35.</note> that who ſo euer ſhall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:183865:24"/> not afflict or humble his ſoule with the reſt, that he will deſtroy them from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his people.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>The time of Faſting, is the time of affliction, either for want of ſome great benefite needfull, or through feeling of ſome great iudgement preſent, or to come.</q> Where the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Faſt muſt paſſe an other condemnation, which maketh no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or choyce of time; but appoynteth euery Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and other ſet Euens yearely, whether the time be proſperous or vnproſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous; whether it be peace or warre, health or ſicknes, dearth or plentie: Which is all one, as if the Phyſition ſhould now appoynt his patient, this day twentie or
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:183865:25"/> fourtie yeares hence, to take a Purgation, or to be let blood: In which caſe, either he muſt be a Prophet, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a Phyſitian, to know that he ſhall on that day, haue need, of it: or elſe he muſt be a Phyſitian of no value, ignorant, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faythfull. As therefore the Phyſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> openeth no vaine, but with obſeruation where the ſigne is; giueth no Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, without heede ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to the time of the yeare, whether it be Spring or Fall; whether it be hot or cold: ſo it behooueth the ſpirituall Phyſitian, to haue an eye vnto the time, when this Medicine is in ſeaſon: And ſo much the more, heere, rather then there; as the danger is greater. For
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:183865:25"/> as a new peece of Cloth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to an olde Garment, taketh ſomething from the olde,<note place="margin">Luke. 5.36.</note> &amp; cauſeth the rent to be worſe then before: ſo Faſting, vnfitly applyed to the ſtate of thoſe that are enioyned to keepe it, maketh them worſe then they were before the Faſt. Yea, that which more is,<note place="margin">Luke. 5.37.</note> as the new Wine put into olde veſſels, doth not onely make them worſe, but breake them all to peeces: So this Faſt thruſt vpon thoſe, which are not, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the time, or for ſome other cauſe apt for it; doeth vtterly deſtroy them. Whereby men may perceiue, what cauſe wee haue to make a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the Popiſh Faſt,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:183865:26"/> as that which is able of it ſelfe (if there were no other corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s amongſt them) to driue a man to eternall deſtruction.</p>
                     <p>According alſo to the greatneſſe of the affliction,<note place="margin">Leui. 23.27, 28.</note> the time of the Faſt is taken, by the diſcretion of thoſe to whom it belongeth; at the leaſt for a whole day. <q>And if the wrath of the Lord be hotter, then two dayes or<note n="*" place="margin">Eſter. 4.16</note> elſe three, as it appeareth by the example of the <hi>Iewes</hi> in <hi>Heſters</hi> time,<note place="margin">Act. 9.9.</note> and of Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> And this time (what ſo euer) hath the nature of a Saboth.<note place="margin">Leuit. 23.30.31.</note> For therein men are bound to abſtaine from their bodily labours, according to the ſame ſtraightneſſe, &amp; with the ſame exceptions, that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:183865:26"/> they are bounde to obſerue the Saboth.<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.12. Leui. 23.32.</note> And therefore the Prophet willeth them to ſanctifie a Faſt. And the Lord threateneth, that who ſo euer ſhall doe any worke on that day, him ſhall he cut off from amongeſt his people. The end whereof is, that men ſetting them ſelues apart from their day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occupations, might be wholly beſtowed in the ſpirituall exerciſes aboue ſpecified.</q> Whereby that we may know, that there was neuer a Thread in the olde Cloth of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Faſt, which was not throughly infected with the ſpirituall leproſie of diſobedience vnto the Lord: It is to be noted, that where they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned many, both wicked
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:183865:27"/> and vnneceſſarie Holy dayes, this * one (and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Saboth, the onely Holy day appointed of the Lord) they quite raſed out of their Kalender. And of the Faſt in generall, thus farre.</p>
                     <p>The kindes or ſortes of Faſtes doe follow: which are either priuate or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.</p>
                     <p>The priuate Faſt is that, which is vndertaken vpon ſome particular calamitie, by the diſcretion of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom the calamitie is ſent. And it is either of a particular man, or houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde. In the former wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it is to be obſerued, that for as much as the Faſt is ioyned with a ſeparation from their dayly occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:183865:27"/> that neither Children, nor Scholers, nor Seruants, nor any other which be at the diſpoſition &amp; gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of others, can chuſe any ſuch day appointed for commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occupations, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of thoſe that haue commaundement ouer them. Without which conſent, they muſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to hold their Faſtes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lordes day, or other dayes of reſt, eſtabliſhed in the places of their abode. For heere the Law of the Lord hath place, that if the Wife, Sonne, or Daughter,<note place="margin">Num. 30.4.</note> vow a Vow vnto the Lord; that the Husband or Father ſhall haue power to breake it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>The publique Faſt is that, which is vndertaken vpon
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:183865:28"/> ſome more generall cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of the Church, at the appoyntment of them, which (vnder Chriſt) haue the gouernement of the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.15.</note> where the faſt is holden.</q> In this Faſt, becauſe a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique aſſembly is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; it followeth, that the chiefe inſtruction of the foreſayd profeſsion of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, is to be fetched from the publique preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word.</p>
                     <p>Now leauing the cauſes of the priuate Faſtes, to the examination of euery one, which can beſt iudge of their owne eſtate; let vs conſider what cauſes there be of a generall Faſt amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt vs. Wherein that it may be ſeene, that the Trumpet of Faſting is blowen rather
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:183865:28"/> by the breath of God, then by the mouth of man: let vs take a ſhort view of the cauſes, of the Faſtes menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the Scriptures.</p>
                     <p>The cauſe of the Faſt, is the wrath of God againſt the Church: where is to be conſidered, that the people of God haue not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded this wrath againſt them ſelues particularly, but againſt others alſo, of the ſame ſocietie &amp; fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in religion that they were of, through a mutuall feeling and compaſsion which they haue one with an other: as in the example of the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Actes. 13.2.</note> whoſe Faſt appeareth to haue been taken in hand, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the miſerie of the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> then
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:183865:29"/> for them ſelues. Now the Churches rounde about vs, being fallen into great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, partly by the ſpirituall miſeries, as well of the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies of <hi>Papiſtes, Arrians, Anabaptiſtes,</hi> the <hi>Familie of loue,</hi> &amp;c. as alſo of the Schiſme of <hi>Lutheraniſme,</hi> dayly preuayling, partly by bodily plagues of the Peſtilence, almoſt in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: of the Sworde in our neighbour countries, and of the Famine which waiteth commonly vpon the ſame: It is euident that thereby groweth one cauſe of hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling our ſelues before our God. And when this wrath is conſidered, either in that which is already come, or in that which may be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhortly to come: to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:183865:29"/> whether ſo euer of the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes we looke, we ſhall finde, that we haue cauſe to Faſt. For what ſpirituall euill is in any of al their Churches, which are not altogeather in ours? not one of thoſe deteſtable Hereſies, but are lodged amongſt vs. And although the Schiſme of <hi>Lutheraniſme</hi> be not among vs, yet there is almoſt a great diſtraction of mindes for the Church gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, beſide the diuerſities of iudgementes in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters. And among bodily puniſhmentes, the Plague hath indifferently fedde, and yet doth feede vpon vs. The Sword hath been ſhaken at vs both in the North by Traytors, and in the South by diſordered
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:183865:30"/> wicked perſons. And ſhold it not ſtrike vs, that her Maieſtie was of late in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of her life by a Shotte? Which that it was not meant towardes her, ought not to abate our care for her maieſtie, but rather encreaſe it: as that which was more neerely directed againſt her of the Lord, to make both her and vs, to cry for his gratious couer and protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ouer her. And if we conſider the wrath that hangeth ouer our heads, the notes thereof are taken by the example of the people of God,<note place="margin">Ezra. 9.3.</note> and firſt of <hi>Ezra,</hi> who vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that the people had married ſtrange women, faſted: where vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wee haue this note of the wrath to come, that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:183865:30"/> conſidering how that ſinne is committed openly in the land in diuers ſortes, that therefore anger is at hand. Here may be handled with godly and diſcreete wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome the Sinnes of the Land.</p>
                     <p>The ſeconde note to know the tempeſt to come, is taken from the <hi>Niniuites</hi> Faſt.<note place="margin">Ionas. 3.5.</note> Wherevpon wee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that for ſo much as we are grieuouſly threatened, as well by the Miniſters and Seruantes of the Lord, that ſpeake in his name vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, as alſo by his late ſhaking of the Earth: that ſharpe iudgement (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentaunce) muſt ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily come vpon vs.</p>
                     <p>The third is taken from ſignes of the wrath of God,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:183865:31"/> which may breake out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs:<note place="margin">Heſter. 4.6.</note> as in <hi>Heſter,</hi> where it was concluded at the requeſt of <hi>Hamon,</hi> of the deſtruction of the whole Church; wherewith may fitly be compared the Holy League (as they ſay) and Decree of the late Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Trent,</hi> againſt the whole Church, and againſt ours particularly.</p>
                     <p>An other ſigne, is the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration made againſt the Church, or an indeauour to execute malice: which draue <hi>Joſaphat</hi> and other moe,<note place="margin">2 Paral. 20.</note> to a Faſt. Here the lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie countenaunces, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duetifull demeanour of the <hi>Papiſtes,</hi> may be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, with their rebellious attemptes in <hi>Ireland;</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Nauie, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:183865:31"/> great preparation made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them of the Holy league, with the troubles in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and Gun-pouder treaſon in <hi>England;</hi> and like accidentes, ſufficient to procure the practiſe of this holy exerciſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:183865:32"/>
                     <head>A GENERAL CONFESSION OF Sinnes, to be made at the exerciſe of Faſting, the more particular confeſsion being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken according to the eſtate of the ſeuerall Churches, by the good diſcretion of the miniſter, vpon the knowledge thereof.</head>
                     <p>O Lord which art glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in power and holineſſe, wee being but Duſt and Aſhes, with the caſting of our ſelues downe, at the foote of thy high Maieſtie: confeſſe that wee are moſt vile ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, conceiued &amp; borne in ſinne, &amp; that we are by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture nothing elſe, but a lumpe of all wickedneſſe, whoſe natural propertie is, to grow in ſin, as wee grow in yeares, &amp; to waxe ſtrong
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:183865:32"/> in wickedneſſe, as the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of our mindes and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies receiue ſtrength. There is in vs, no holeſome nor ſounde knowledge how to obey: there is no manner of good will or affection to pleaſe thee: finally, there dwelleth no good thing in our fleſh. And although our curſed eſtate doth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in greatly appeare, yet our ſinne is made out of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſinfull, through the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding grace which thou offereſt by the Goſpell of thy deare Sonne; whereby wee are ſo farre from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting, that of our ſelues we ſhould waxe worſe and worſe. For the more light of knowledge is ſhewed, the blinder would we remaine: the greater obedience is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:183865:33"/> taught, the frowarder and ſtubberner would wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, if thou by the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie working of thy holy ſpirite, ſhouldeſt not cauſe it to be fruitfull. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we haue this natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall corruption in common, with the whole rotten race of <hi>Adam;</hi> yet wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that in vs it hath bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp; ſhot foorth ſo much more then in others, as we haue had moe meanes to kil it, and to cauſe it to wither, then others haue had. Where firſt of all, the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious offer of the treaſure of thy holy Goſpell vnto vs, maketh vs guiltie many waies. For where paſsing by many other nations, thou haſt truſted our natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: yet with a number of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:183865:33"/> vs, hath it found as ſmall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, and felt as great reſiſtance, as amongſt them, at whoſe Gates it neuer knocked. For a great porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the land, partly neuer yeelding them ſelues to the obedience therof; and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falling from it, after they had once yeelded; ſtande proudly as it were at the ſtaues end with thee. The reſt which make profeſsion of their ſubmittaunce vnto it, doe it not accordingly. For firſt, there be heapes of our people, which either through an yrckſomneſſe of the yron-yoke of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> Religion, or through a wicked opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they nouriſh, of embracing any Religion ſet foorth; ſo caſt aſide the former <hi>Poperie,</hi> as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:183865:34"/> they ſtil abide in an vtter ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the truth it ſelfe; in ſuch ſort,) that through want of Preaching) they are as raw in the knowledge of the true ſeruice of thee, as they were expert before, in the ſeruice of the Deuill. And where knowledge is, to any ſuch ſufficiencie as is requiſite for the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the kingdome of Heauen: there is it (for a great part) ioyned with ſuch hypocriſie, as maketh them more deteſtable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, (which ſearcheſt the very Raines,) then if they had ſtill continued in their ignoraunce. Now, for the remnant of vs, which through Grace, haue truly and faythfully beleeued, it is with ſo great weakneſſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:183865:34"/> of Fayth, and ſo ſmall refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Manners; that our glorious profeſsion of the Goſpell, ſupported and borne out with ſo ſmall ſhew of the fruites, which the excellencie thereof doth require, maketh not onely the enimies to condemne vs, but our ſelues to ſuſpect one another, whether wee belong vnto thee or no. Wherein, O Lord, wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that to be our great and horrible ſinne, that being put in truſt with this vnſpeakable treaſure of thy holy Goſpell, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to our neighbours, profeſſours about vs; yet we are in thankfull obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto thee, behind them all: firſt, in knowledge; laſt, in zeale: before them in the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:183865:35"/> doctrine of thy holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; behinde them in the diſcipline of the ſame. The yoke of the ſlauerie of our bodyes, which the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Religion layed vpon vs, we willingly ſhake off: but the holy bandes of thy Law, whereby our riotous life and affections, ſhould be brought into bondage, wee do hardly, and heauily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte. The Goſpell which brought a freer vſe of our lawfull honors, pleaſures &amp; commodities, was welcome vnto vs: but the ſame Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, which reſtraineth the vnlawfull licentiouſneſſe of our ambition, intemperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and couetouſneſſe, is not ſo. Finally ſo much of the Goſpel, as doth more neere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſpect our ſaluation, we
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:183865:35"/> ſeeme to haue ſome care to retaine: but ſo much of it as doth more directly reſpect thy glorie, and the profite one of an other, (thoſe eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially which are not of the ſame lande with vs) wee make ſmall accompt off. And ſeeing the naked trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the holy Goſpell, had beene a rich reward of a moſt ſeruiceable ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: it comming vnto vs not alone, but accompanied with ſo long a peace, with ſo great a wealth, ſo plenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful aboundance of al things, as this Land hath neuer or ſeldome vſed, other Landes about vs haue long looked after: maketh our guilt a great deale more, becauſe that in thy ſo great a largis towards vs, we haue been
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:183865:36"/> ſo vngratious towards thee againe. Here therefore is an other Stayer, whereby our ſinne clymeth higher: For that wee, in the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this life, ſurmounting our aunceſtours of the ſame profeſsion of the Goſpell, in King <hi>Henrie</hi> and King <hi>Edwardes</hi> time; are, for the fruites that ſuch a liberalitie asketh at our hands, a great deale worſe then they: and going beyond (other landes in theſe outward bleſsinges, are out-run of them, euen in the very outwarde teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and tokens of our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience towardes thee. And beſides this huge heape, and (as it were) reeke, of our generall &amp; common ſinnes, we haue to confeſſe (at the barre of thy iudgement
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:183865:36"/> ſeate) the particular ſinnes that we haue kocked vp in our ſeuerall eſtates. For our gouernours, O Lord, for the moſt part, beeing more mindfull of the fulfilling of their affections, then either of thy glory, or of their good eſtate, which are committed vnto them, haue not helde ſo ſteadie a hande as they ought to haue done, either for the ſtabliſhing of the Lawes, by which (vnder thee) they ſhould haue ruled vs; and we by them, ſhould haue bin gouerned of thee; or for the thorough execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo many, and ſo farre foorth as they haue been wel eſtabliſhed. Our Iudges and other Miniſters of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice likewiſe, haue either ignorantly, or corruptly
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:183865:37"/> declyned from righteous iudgement: or giuing ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for the trueth, they haue done it (diuers of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) with no conſcience of thy true feare, or loue of trueth; but for reſpect, either of vaine glorie, or of perſons. The Miniſters, which ſhould haue been Lightes vnto all eſtates, haue for the moſt part, no light in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: and their eſtate, in whoſe good conſtitution and ſound health, the reſt ſhould haue recouered their health, is of all other, the moſt ſicke vnto death. For if the whole number be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed, ſcarce the hundred wil be found, to be in the lot of a faythfull Miniſterie. For ah alas, how many are there, which occupying the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:183865:37"/> place of Ambaſſadours, ei: ther for want of abilitie, or for that they loue eaſe and ſleepe, carrie no tollerable Ambaſſage at all: how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie which carrying the light of the Goſpell in their mouthes, carry alſo in their handes, the filthy water of ambition &amp; coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe to quench it with. And thoſe which by thy grace, are for their might and will in ſome good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure iuſtifiable: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, for the moſt part, beare it with ſuch infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, through ſlippes, aſwell in a ſound and ſubſtantiall maner of teaching, as alſo in an euen life anſwering ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, that if thy bleſſing were not marueilous vpon their labours, we ſhould not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:183865:38"/> need to feare, the quenching of this fire of the holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, kindled among vs, by the enemies: as that which hauing ſo ſmall attendance of blowing, would die of it ſelfe. Finally, the people beare ſo ſmall loue vnto their Gouernours of all ſortes, in loue ſo ſmall reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, &amp; in them both ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle willing obedience: that it may be not (vneaſely) ſeene, that all the practiſe of the Church and common wealth, haue conſpired to prouoke thee Lord againſt them. Theſe our great and ouergrowen ſinnes, albeit they are gotten aboue our heades, yet reſt they not heere. For where thou haſt by thy holy Seruantes, the Miniſters of thy bleſſed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:183865:38"/> worde, ſharpely chidden with vs, and in a ſeuere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of thy iudgments due vnto them, fearefully threatened vs for them: yet haue we not trembled at thy voyce; at which the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes doe melte, and the Rockes doe rent aſunder. A ſtrange thing, that the Lion ſhould roare, and the weake Lambes ſhould not be affraide: that the Lord of Hoaſtes ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime Warre againſt vs, &amp; we ſhould not goe foorth and meete him, for intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of peace. Nay, his wrath (as hath been ſhewed) hath been, and yet is kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt vs: and yet as ſenceleſſe men, and as dead fleſh we are not mooued. Wee are pricked, and wee
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:183865:39"/> feele it not. Wee are woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and wee doe not ſo much as aske, Who hath ſtricken vs? The tempeſt that is comming towarde vs, threateneth our vtter drowning: and yet as a drunken man, we lie ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the verie toppe of the Maſt. Whereby it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent againſt our ſelues, that vnto the multitude of our ſinnes, wee haue added an other degree of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; which is, the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuaunce in them: vnto our diſobedience, we haue ioyned ſtubborneſſe, and the Byles and Botches of our rebellion, being ougly in thy ſight, doe through the putrifaction &amp; feſtred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them, caſt out ſuch ſtincke, as the earth which
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:183865:39"/> we tread vpon, the waters which we drinke, and the ayre which we breath, are tainted and poyſoned with the infection of them. Yea Lord, taught by the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull iuſtice of thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Law, we charge vpon our heads all the ſinnes of our Fathers and Graund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, to the vttermoſt of our generations which are paſt: as thoſe wherevnto wee are iuſter inheritours, then vnto any Landes or Goods that they haue left vs. Whereby it falleth out againſt vs, that our ſinnes touch the Cloudes; yea, breake into the Heauens of thy Maieſties owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence: whoſe meaſure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alreadie (as it ſeemeth) filled, there remaineth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:183865:40"/> but that it ſhould be turned vpon our heades. wherevpon wee make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſelues an other confeſſion, that we are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of all the benefites of this life, or of the life to come: both thoſe which wee either haue, or yet hope to enioy, from the greateſt to the ſmaleſt; from the kingdome of heauen, to one onely drop of Water. That we are worthie of all the Plagues, which either haue heretofore ceaſed, or been yet poſſeſſed of vs. Yea if thou ſhouldeſt ranſake all the hid, and ſecret treaſures of thy fearefull iudgmentes, which in thy Lawe thou threatneſt againſt the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers thereof, not only to the raſing and ſweeping
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:183865:40"/> vs from the face of the earth, but alſo to the throwing of vs headlong into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pitte of hell: yet would we therein alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thy righteous iudgementes: for vnto vs belongeth ſhame &amp; confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of faces, but vnto thee, glory and righteouſneſſe. All which both guilt of ſinne, and deſert of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, notwithſtanding, (O father of mercies, and God of all comfort) wee truſting vnto the Promiſes which thou haſt made vs in Ieſus Chriſt, are bold through him, humbly to call for the performaunce of them. And firſt we humbly deſire thee, to forgiue vs all our ſinnes. Thou haſt ſaid, that if wee confeſſe our ſinnes, thou art
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:183865:41"/> faithfull to forgiue vs them. We acknowledge the debt, cancell therefore the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation: let not the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of them preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs; but where our ſinne hath abounded, let thy grace more abound; and as we haue multiplyed our ſinnes, ſo wee pray thee to multiply thy mercies: and although we haue by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in them, ſo ſoaked our ſelues, that thereby we are not onely lightly ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but alſo haue gotten as it were the Scarlet and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple die of them: yet let them all (wee pray thee,) beeing waſhed in the blood of thy deare Sonne, be made as white as the Snow in <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> &amp; as the Woolle of the Sheepe which come from
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:183865:41"/> waſhing.</p>
                     <p>And to conclude as our ſinnes haue magnified the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in an infinite length, breadth, depth, and height, ſo let thy mercies (which paſſe all vnderſtanding,) of all ſides, and all aſſaies, out-reach them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo wee moſt humblie deſire thee, ô Lord, that the ſinne being pardoned, thy wrath, which is alreadie declared, may be appeaſed towardes all the Churches of our profeſsion, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie towardes vs, that the manifolde breaches of the Churches and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthes may bee made vp, that thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing receiued into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the Church, which belong to thy electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:183865:42"/> the reſt of the <hi>Papiſtes</hi> &amp; <hi>Heretikes,</hi> may be vtterly rooted out; and that the enimies in religion, being ſlaine, we may to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt thinke all one thing, in the honeſt and peaceable gouernement of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. Vpon which vniting of vs in all trueth and honeſtie, the curſes of the Plague, and barrenneſſe being remooued, a way may be made to thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges; which (as the Hilles doe the Vallies) may make our land holeſomely fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And that not onely the wrath which is alreadie kindled, may be quenched, but that which hath been lately threatened, may be cauſed to retyre. For the graunt wherof vnto vs, we
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:183865:42"/> beſeech thee to remember, that how vnworthy ſoeuer, yet are we thy people, &amp; the Sheepe of thy paſture, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt redeemed with thy moſt precious blood, watched ouer with a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eye, defended with a mightie hand: deſpiſe not therfore, ô Lord, the works of thy handes. And ſeeing thou haſt loued vs, when we hated thee; viſited vs, when we deſired thee not; then acknowledged vs, when we knew not thee: now that there be a number of vs, which loue thee, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thine aboade, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thee: hold on thy loue ſtill, depart not from vs, deny vs not, ô thou God of trueth, which art the God that changeſt not.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:183865:43"/> And if thou wouldeſt or couldeſt forget vs, calling vpon thee: yet what ſhould become of thy great name, which is called vpon by vs? And therefore for thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſake, and for thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed names ſake, which in our deſtruction ſhould be rent and runne through; ſpare vs, ſpare vs, good Lord, according to the vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all dealing, which thou haſt euer kept with thoſe, which in prayer haue had recourſe vnto thee; and according to the old and vnchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able nature, of a mercifull, kind, ſparing, and long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering God. Which mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie wee doe not (ô Lord) deſire, to the end that wee ſhould tumble and wallow our ſelues in our accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:183865:43"/> neglect, and contempt of thy holy word: but to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with mercie for our ſinnes, and the rewarde of them, wee moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie craue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the knees of our heartes; that for the time to come, (how long or how ſhort ſoeuer) wee with deniall and deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſelues, and of our wicked luſtes, may offer vp vnto thee in Ieſus Chriſt, our ſelues, our bodies and ſoules, to be ſeruantes at thy holy commaundement, in that reaſonable ſeruice, which the high reaſon of thy holy word doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe: and to be weapons, or inſtrumentes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and holineſſe, as they haue been heretofore, of the contrarie.</p>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:183865:44"/>
                     <p>All which thinges, as what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou knoweſt to be further needfull for vs, or for any of the Churches, we pray thee, as our Sauiour hath taught. &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:183865:44"/>
                     <head>A Confeſsion of Sinnes, with Faith <hi>and Repentance.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>O Mercifull and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, we thy ſeruantes doe hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly proſtrate our ſelues before thy Maieſtie, ackowledging heere in thy ſight, our hainous offences committed againſt thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, ſeeing &amp; beholding thy heauie wrath againſt them: We feele our ſelues laden (ô Lord our God) with a huge companie of horrible ſinnes, wherof euen the very leaſt, (being but conceiued in thought,) is ſufficient in iudgement, to throw vs down to the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting burning lake. Our
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:183865:45"/> owne conſciences (ô Lord) doe beare witneſſe againſt vs, of our manifolde tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsions of thy bleſſed Law, of our ſecuritie and ſenceleſſe blindneſſe, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning headlong to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting ſinne after ſinne, although not notorious to the world, yet horrible before thine eye. The thoughtes of our hearts riſe vp in iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs: the vanitie of our talke before thy Maieſtie, condemneth vs: the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of our deeds from thy ſight, reiecteth vs: all our wicked thoughtes, wordes, and deedes, with the inwarde corruption of our nature, doe altogeather as it were a whole lumpe and load of ſinne, lie heauie
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:183865:45"/> vpon vs, and with their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable weight, doe euen preſſe vs downe to Hell.</p>
                     <p>We doe daily grone vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the burthen of them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting our owne follie, ſo greedily running into them. In heauen, earth, or hell, we ſee none able to ſuſtaine the weight of them, but euen thy dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, who in mercie infinite, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion endles, hath ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ouercome that endleſſe puniſhment due vnto them: in him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in him moſt mercifull Father, and through him, wee come to thee, beeing fully aſſured according to thy promiſe, that thou wilt accept and take that full recompence, which hee
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:183865:46"/> thy deare Sonne hath made for vs, as a iuſt ranſome for all the ſinnes of all thoſe, who with a true fayth take hold on him. In him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſee thine anger to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs appeaſed, thy wrath ſatisfied, &amp; our debts paied.</p>
                     <p>Increaſe in vs, (good Lord) we beſeech thee, this liuely and feeling Fayth; for we feele it oftentimes in vs very weake, and troubled with many doubtes: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it in vs (ô Lord,) that we may through thy holy ſpirite be aſſured, that the puniſhment of our ſinnes is fully in thy Sonne diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. Make vs, ô Lord our God, to feele this ſame in our ſoules and conſciences, that Ieſus Chriſt is ours,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:183865:46"/> and all that he hath done: that we are grafted into his body, and made one with him; and therefore fellow heires with him of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life. Let vs not onely haue theſe wordes in our mouthes (good Lord) but through thy holy ſpirit, let vs feele the comfort of them in our heartes fully ſealed, and ſetled in vs: that wee feeling our ſelues inwardly before thy iudgement ſeate diſcharged, and our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences towardes thee appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; may be ſwallowed vp with an vnfaigned loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thy heauenly Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and towardes our brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren for thy ſake. Make ſinne to die in vs dayly more and more, that wee may hate, deteſt, and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:183865:47"/> abhorre all ſinne &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe in all men, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in our ſelues: that we may ſtrongly (through thy holy ſpirite) ſet our ſelues in open warre and defiance againſt all ſinne &amp; wickednes; that we pleaſe not our ſelues in our ſinnes, but ſtraightly examining ſinne by the iuſt rule of thy holy Lawes, we may vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the bottome of our heartes, condemne euen the leaſt ſinne in our ſelues, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing our whole ioy, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and conſolation vpon thoſe thinges which be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable to thy bleſſed will, alwayes being afraide to doe any thing contrarie to the ſame: that wee may euen from the bottome of our heartes, examine and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:183865:47"/> trie our thoughtes before thy preſence, that they be vpright and vnfaigned, not hypocriticall in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſhew onely, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearaunce, but that euen all corners of our heartes being opened and diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before thee, wee may euen as though it were openly before the face of the whole World, bring them in ſhew, knowing that a double heart is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable in thy ſight: and that wee may walke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes as before thine eyes; not only before the eyes of man, being more carefull to walke circumſpectly, in this reſpect, that we haue thee to be a viewer of our doings, a thouſande-folde more then the eyes of man:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:183865:48"/> that thus we may walke as becommeth thy children, not onely in outward ſhew, but alſo in ſinceritie of hart, abhorring euen the leaſt ſinne in our ſelues; ſtriuing, reſiſting, and fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne, not delighting our ſelues in ſinne, nor nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing the ſame in our breſt, but earneſtly embrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſtudiouſly ſeeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after thoſe things which be pleaſant in thine eyes: that neither the feare of man, nor loſſe of goods, life, landes, poſſeſſions, or friends, draw vs away from thee, to doe any the leaſt thing contrary to thy will and pleaſure: neither the fauour or friendſhippe of man, nor yet the flattering enticement of this world,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:183865:48"/> nor the vaine promotions of the ſame, doe mooue vs any whit from the true and endleſſe ioy, delight, and pleaſure which wee ought to haue in thoſe thinges which be agreeable to thy will, and the conſtant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the ſame: but that alwayes to the end of our life we may continue in thy pathes, growing and increaſing from faith to fayth, from ſtrength to ſtrength, till at the length we ſhall come to thy euerlaſting reſt. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:183865:49"/>
                     <head>A Prayer for the KING.</head>
                     <p>O Gratious Lord, and moſt mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thee the Lord of Lordes, and the King of Kinges, creating at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, &amp; ruling all things euermore in Heauen and Earth, according to thy wonderfull wiſedome and power: and our ſelues to be thy poore ſeruantes, the worke of thy hands, and the ſheepe of thy paſture, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected to thy Maieſtie, and depending vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouidence for al things. Neuertheleſſe, ſeeing thou in thy wiſedome annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Kinges and Queenes,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:183865:49"/> appointing them to rule ouer thy people, to ſit as Lieutenants in thy ſeate, to miniſter iuſtice, and moſt of all, as Fathers and Nurſes to maintaine and cheariſh thy Church; commanding vs not onely to obey &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them: but moreouer to pray for them, as watching ouer vs for our good. We therefore beſeech thee for thy great mercies ſake, and for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, to ſhew thy mercy to al Kings and princes, that maintaine thy glorious Goſpell: but eſpecially we pray thee to bleſſe our gratious King, in all ſpirituall bleſsinges in Chriſt Ieſus; and in all temporall bleſsinges, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy good pleaſure, that in the great meaſures of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:183865:50"/> thy effectuall loue, he may more and more finde great increaſe of vertue, &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; ſtrength in Chriſt Ieſus, to the faythfull and happy diſcharge of his due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that his holieneſſe, and ioy, and zeale of thy houſe, may be multiplied, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting.</p>
                     <p>And ſeeing it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee, of thy ſingular mercy, to giue him this ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall honour, miraculouſly deliuering him out of the handes of his enimies, to ſet a double Crowne vpon his head, and to make him the inſtrument to aduaunce thy glory, &amp; Goſpell amongſt vs. As wee giue thee moſt heartie thanks for theſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular benefites, ſo we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee to make him and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:183865:50"/> vs euermore thankefull for it, and in thy good pleaſure ſtill to preſerue him, for the continuance of theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges towardes vs, with all increaſe from time to time, to thy glory, the benefite of the Church, and his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite peace in Chriſt Ieſus, the prince of peace. And furthermore, wee pray thee for him, and the eſtate, that ſuch as be enimies of the Goſpell, and his enimies alſo, for the defence thereof, may not deſpiſe the peace offered them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, but that they may account thy long ſuffering, and his peaceable and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloudy gouernement, an occaſion of ſaluation to their ſoules, and vnfeined loue to the trueth, and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:183865:51"/> their mercifull ſoueraigne. Otherwiſe if they ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine diſobedient to the trueth, diſobedient to his Highneſſe and daungerous to the State; then (O God of our Saluation) as thou haſt diſcouered them, ſo diſcouer them ſtill; as thou haſt preuented them, ſo preuent them ſtill; and let their eyes waxe weary with looking, and their heartes faint with wayting for the comming of that, which yet commeth not, neither let it come (O Lord) we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, but a bleſſed and a long raigne to him, and peace to <hi>Sion</hi> for euermore. Alſo (deare father) ſo bleſſe, ſo loue, ſo in thy ſpirite ſanctifie and keepe him, that he may in the ſpirit of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:183865:51"/> counſell and fortitude ſo rule that other ſiſter alſo, namely this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, that they may flouriſh to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, and grow vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as Palme trees, in beautie, and in ſtrength, giuing ayde and helpe one to an other; that in the Church the glory of God may appeare, as the Sunne in his brightneſſe, and that the lande may flow with Milke and Honie, and true peace abound therein, as in the triumphant reigne of <hi>Salomon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe garces (O Lord) are great, and we miſerable ſinners, vnworthie of the leaſt of them: therefore looke not to vs, but to thy ſelfe; not to our iniquities, but to thy great mercies,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:183865:52"/> accepting the death &amp; paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thy Sonne, as a full ranſome for al our offences: throwing them into the bottome of the Sea, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Croſſe and Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection effectuall in vs to al obedience and godlineſſe, as becommeth thy Saintes: that to all other thy good bleſsings towards our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Soueraigne; this may be added, that he gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth bleſſedly, ouer a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed people, a people bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the Lord, and belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the Lord; &amp; that thy graces may abounde as the warers of the Sea, in the King, and in the people; in the Church, and in the Common wealth, from day to day, till the day of our tranſlation into thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:183865:52"/> where iuſtice Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biteth; where alſo we ſhall inhabite and reigne with thee, according to thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, for euer. Graunt theſe things (O mercifull Father) for thy deare Sonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſt his ſake: in whoſe name, we craue them at thy mercifull hand, praying furthermore for them, as he hath raught vs to pray. Our Father which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:183865:53"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:183865:53"/>
                  <p>The ſubſtance of the <hi>Lordes Supper.</hi> Shortly and ſoundly ſet foorth; togeather, with the <hi>principall poyntes in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie,</hi> concerning that <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, ſufficiently diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> for the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and comfort of all Chriſtian readers. Neceſſarie to be read at all times, but eſpecially, before the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the ſayd Supper.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</bibl>
                     <p>Prooue your ſelues, whether yee are in the fayth: examine your ſelues. Know yee not your owne ſelues, how that Ieſus Chriſt is in you, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye be reprobates?</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>T. Man.</hi> and <hi>I. Hariſon, Anno.</hi> 1610.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:183865:54"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:183865:54"/>
                  <head>To the right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and my verie good friendes, ſir <hi>William Peliam</hi> Knight, her Maieſties Lieuetenant of the Ordinance; and the Ladie <hi>Dorothie</hi> his wife, <hi>T.VV.</hi> wiſheth in this life, all ſound knowledge of Gods trueth, with an aſſured fayth in the trueth of his promiſes: and after the weariſome dayes of this pilgrimage ſhall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, eternall bl ſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the life to come, through Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongeſt many reaſons, (need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe nowe to rehearſe) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing mee, to offer this ſmal Treatiſe vnto your Worſhippes; this was not the leaſt, to weet, that thereby, I might teſtifie, as my vnfeigned good will
<pb facs="tcp:183865:55"/> towardes you in the Lord, ſo the care that I haue in all holy loue, to buyld you vp in the ſincere iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the pointes and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſtian religion. For, though I doubt not, but that you are in ſome good meaſure endued, with ſundry good giftes and graces form God, which ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall ſpurres and prouocations vnto you, to imploy your ſelues to the vttermoſt of your powers, in the ſeruice of his Maieſtie, and the obedience of his will: yet, in reſpect of the corruption of mans nature, and the ſtumbling blockes, which Sathan our common aduerſarie ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in our way, to hinder vs, in the raſe and courſe of godlineſſe I know that all Gods children, and therefore you amongeſt the reſt, haue neede of continuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers, not onely to put you in minde, but alſo to prouoke you, to paſſe the dayes of your pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in the reuerent feare of Gods great Maieſtie: and being ſound in zeale, ſincere in knowledge, and carefull in practiſe, to finiſh your courſe in his fayth, that ſo at the
<pb facs="tcp:183865:55"/> laſt, you may be made thorough Chriſt, partakers of eterrall ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is the end of our hope a d fayth, yea, the verie ende of our life in this life: and therefore good reaſon, that wee ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy our whole life thereto, and to the continuall vſe &amp; practiſe, of all the meanes that God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined for our better attayning thereof, and namely that we ſhould be often and earneſt with him in prayer: that we ſhould delight in, and labour to profite by the daily hearing, reading, meditating, and conference of &amp; in his holy word; and that wee ſhould frequent the reuerent and ordinarie vſe of his Sacramentes, appoynted for the ſtrengthening of our fayth, in the trueth of his promiſes, growing, euen to this narrowneſſe and ſtreightneſſe of onſcience, that we ſhould thinke euery day and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hower of a day ill ſpent, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we haue not profited ſomewhat towardes godlineſſe and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</p>
                  <p>True is it, that here is handled but onely one poynt of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion:
<pb facs="tcp:183865:56"/> yet notwithſtanding, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech your Worſhippes, by this to gather the readie good will that is and ſhall bee in mee, through Gods goodneſſe: further to write or ſpeake, in this, or any other ground, whereby your knowledge may be increaſed, and your fayth ſtrengthened in the trueth of Gods eternall Word and Promiſes: yea, I doe further requeſt you, and in you, all thoſe that ſhall read this little Diſcourſe, to conſider, not the ſmalneſſe of the Treatie, but the waightineſſe of the matter propounded in the ſame, which is one of the principles of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, wherein wee cannot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt without our great hurt: and to which wee can not vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily repaire (a fault ouer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in theſe our dayes,) without iudgement and condemnation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our owne ſoules: which hath made mee to annex at the ende thereof, ſundry ſhort medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, for the better direction of the ignoraunt and vnskilfull in this behalfe.</p>
                  <p>In all this that I write, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb facs="tcp:183865:56"/> it bee, I deale with them (I hope) that be both charitable and wiſe inough to conceaue my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and therfore ſhall not neede to vſe many words to perſwade that, wherevnto you your ſelues bee in ſome meaſure, thorough Gods goodneſſe, inclined, and to the perfourmaunce whereof you are bound, by the great grace and excellent calling, that the ſame God in mercie hath beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you.</p>
                  <p>This onely I wiſh, and will pray or, all the dayes of my life, that this my poore labour, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer other thing elſe it ſhall pleaſe him, by me or any other to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, either for your good, or the good of his Saintes whereſoeuer, may be profitable, not vnto you onely for your ſaluation, but vnto all his elect and choſen children, that the number of his faythfull being accompliſhed, and the dayes of ſinne vtterly cut off, wee may be gathered to thoſe eternall and heauenly Tabernacles, which Chriſt our ſauiour hath purchaſed and prepared for vs: and that wee
<pb facs="tcp:183865:57"/> might be the better aſſured there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is entred before hand there into, to take poſſeſsion thereof in our name: there to raigne with him for euer, and euer. So be it.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips alwayes readie and humble in Chriſt, <hi>T. VV.</hi> the Lords moſt vnworthy ſeruant.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:183865:57"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the motion and requeſt of ſundrie my deare friendes in the Lord, I haue thought good to putte dovvne tvvo Prayers at the latter ende of this Treatiſe, not thereby min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding either to tie any perſon to the vſe of them onely, for they may accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſeuerall neceſſi ies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſome other of their ovvne, or practiſe ſome better forme already ſet dovvne, by men of greater giftes, and feeling: nor yet, ſo to buſie their mindes, and to occupie their heades, as that they should be imployed in theſe, vvhen the publike Prayers and exerciſes of the Church, performed by the Miniſters are in hand (for be it farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, vvhen the Miniſter Gods mouth ſpeaketh from the Lord to vs or vvhen he as our mouth ſpeaketh to the Lord for vs, to haue either our heartes
<pb facs="tcp:183865:58"/> or our mouthes occupied about any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, than the reuerent hearing and conſenting vnto, of ſuch thinges as he vttereth) but that ayding the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of our breathren, ſuch as haue not the gifte to conceiue Prayer, might haue a forme to exerciſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in, both before they repaire to the publike exerciſes of the Church, and after the celebration of thoſe reuerent my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, ſhall he finiſhed.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:183865:58"/>
                  <head>The ſubſtaunce of the Lordes Supper, ſhorly and ſoundly ſet foorth, for the inſtruction and comfort of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian readers.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O cleare, yea, to voyde all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time haue crept into the Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the matter of the Lordes ſupper, theſe three circumſtances, in the firſt place are meete to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt, who ordeined it; to witte, Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour, which is an euident proofe of his eternall Deitie or Godhead, becauſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to God alone, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute and ordeine Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:183865:59"/> in the Church.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, when it was inſtituted, to wit, before his death and ſuffering, by which it is plaine, that the bread in the ſupper, cannot be the ſame naturall body, that was borne of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Marie, crucified on the Croſſe, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, wherefore it was ordeined, to witt, for the ſtrengthening of our faith in the trueth of Gods promiſes, and to put vs in remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Ieſus Chriſt abſent: now a remembrance of a thing it could not bee, if the thing it ſelfe were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. And all theſe three pointes are prooued out of 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11. verſ. 23.24.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 In the ſecond place, the conſideration of theſe three
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:183865:59"/> circumſtaunces following, will ſerue much for the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the queſtion alſo.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt, which be the ſignes in the Sacrament, to wit, Bread and Wine, which haue that nature and force in them, not of themſelues, for then all Bread and Wine ſhould haue the like; but in reſpect of the Lordes inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, who alone hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to ordeine ſignes or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, and to giue them that effect and propertie.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, what be the things ſignified thereby, to witt, the bleſſed body of Chriſt crucified, and his precious bloud ſhed, for the benefite and good of all thoſe that by a liuely and ſtedfaſt faith, do apprehend and take hold of him and all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:183865:60"/> his merites.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, the analogie, proportion and agreement, which is between the ſignes and the things ſignified, the Lord no doubt chooſing ſuch elements as might moſt aptly and fitly expreſſe the thinges ſignified and ſealed by the ſame. Which like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe may be brought into three eſpeciall heades or pointes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt, that as verily as that Bread is broken, and the wine defuſed or ſpread abroade, becauſe many bee partakers of it: ſo verily was Chriſt wounded for our tranſgreſsions, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for our iniquities, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, Cap. 53.5. and his body crucified, and his blood ſhed vpon the croſſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:183865:60"/> for many, for the remiſsion of ſinnes. <hi>Math.</hi> 26.26.22.28. 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11.24.25.26.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, that as Bread hath his propertie through Gods bleſsing giuen it, to feede and ſtrengthen our naturall bodies in this life: ſo his body being repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented effectually vnto vs by that bread; hath the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame propertie, touching our ſoules, to ſtrengthen and to nouriſh them ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. And euen as the Wine comfort and make mans heart glad, as appeareth by ſundry. Scriptures: ſo our full ioy and ſpirituall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is, to be found in him alone. And (to ioyne theſe two togeather, of which we haue ſpoken ſeuerally) this wee muſt know and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:183865:61"/> beleeue further, that as our diet is then full, whole, and perfect, as it were, when it conſiſteth of theſe two thinges, Bread and Wine, or Drinke: ſo wee might know, that the fulneſſe and prefection of all ſpirituall nouriſhment is to be found in Chriſt alone, &amp; no where elſe, whileſt that hee is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, as well the Drincke, as the Meate of our ſoule, not onely in this double ſigne, helping our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as it were, but alſo tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vs to ſeeke the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly refection and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of our ſoules, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wholly in him, and no where elſe. Wherevnto alſo he him ſelfe in ſome ſort alludeth. <hi>Math. 11.</hi> verſ. <hi>28.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ioh. 6, 35. Ioh. 7.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:183865:61"/> 37.38.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, that as the Bread is made of many Graines, and the Wine of ſundry &amp; ſeuerall Grapes, and yet all make but one Bread and one Wine: ſo all the faythfull ſhould be inſtructed thereby, that though they be ſeuerall and diſtinct perſons one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from an other, as the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the body are, yet they all compacted togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, make but one body; as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> plainely prooueth, <hi>Rom. 12.4 5.</hi> but ſpecially, <hi>1. Corinth. 10.16, 17.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe three things then, out of all that hitherto hath been ſpoken, I would haue to be obſerued and noted.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt, that though it be true, that euen by the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:183865:62"/> of the Goſpell, wee receiue Chriſt with all his benefites, of which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh <hi>Galat. 3, 1.</hi> that Chriſt was deſcribed in their ſight, and crucified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; yet that wee haue this, more plainely and plentifully ſet foorth vnto vs in the vſe of the Supper, whileſt that we by fayth feeding on him, that is the Bread of life, which came downe from heauen. <hi>John 6.51.</hi> are by that means become bone of his bones, and fleſh of his fleſh, <hi>Epheſ. 5.30.</hi> and made one in him, euen as the Father and hee are one. <hi>John. 17.21.22.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, that this holy Sacrament, doeth not onely direct vs to the death and paſsion of our Sauiour
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:183865:62"/> Chriſt, which was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med many hundred yeares agoe, as the one &amp; the onely Sacrifice for ſinne, neuer to be reiterated; becauſe that thereby he being the onely High prieſt and eternall Sacrificer, hath conſecrated for euer all them that are ſanctified: <hi>Hebr. 9.28. Heb. 10.14.</hi> but alſo, yea chiefly and eſpecially, to the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious fruites and effectes, that we receaue thereby: as the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, the aſſured pledge of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, and ſuch like: which are liuely ſet foorth, and preached vnto vs in the ſame, to the ende that wee may bee made partakers thereof.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, that we muſt know and beleeue, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:183865:63"/> though this Sacrament doe ſpecially and chiefly direct vs to Chriſt, his death, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, obedience, and the fruites thereof: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding alſo, it doeth inſtruct vs of the ſpeciall dueties of Loue, that in Chriſt, and for Chriſt, wee as the members of that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, whereof he is the onely head, ought vnfeignedly to performe, one of vs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an other, not onely as profitable and neceſſarie for the partes, to whom ſuch duties are performed, but comfortable alſo to our ſelues, whileſt by that, as by a badge or cognizaunce, we are knowne to be Chriſtes Diſciples, <hi>Iohn 13.35.</hi> and haue ſealed vp in our hearts, the free pardon and full for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:183865:63"/> of all our ſinnes, &amp; an aſſured pledge of our tranſlation out of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe into light: ſee <hi>Luke. 7.47.</hi> Alſo <hi>1. John 3.14.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the third place for the clearing of this controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, we muſt haue a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eye to Sathans ſubtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, who laboureth in this poynt, as in all other points of Chriſtian religion, by extreamities to draw vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all corruption. Now the extreameneſſes that in time hertofore, haue burſt foorth and are yet in many places ſtoutly and ſtiffely main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, are ſpecially three.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt, that of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, who holde and defende, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the Supper left vs, ſaue the bare and naked
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:183865:64"/> ſignes of Chriſtes death and paſsion. But the trueth is ſo farre off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> allowing this, that we feare not to affirme, that beſides the ſignes, wee haue the thinges them ſelues ſignified, truly and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally exhibited vnto vs; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is moſt certaine that our Sauiour Chriſt who is the trueth it ſelfe and can not lye, doeth in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deed and aſſuredly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh vnto vs, all the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which he made vnto vs, and ſealed vnto vs, by the vſe of the ſignes in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament, making vs parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers euen of his very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, that we might alſo grow vp into one life with him. And though this can not be comprehended by the eye of mans reaſon and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:183865:64"/> vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, yet we know that this is ſenſibly ſet foorth vnto vs, by ſeuerall meanes and inſtrumentes: ſome outward, as the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes in the Sacrament; and ſome inwarde, as the ſpirituall Grace repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereby. For we are not Angels, but men, conſiſting of bodie and ſoule: and therefore the Lord by the vſe of his Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, hath prouided for both partes; as the Word for our Eares; and our Eares for hearing of the ſame, that ſo Fayth might be wrought in our heartes. <hi>Rom. 10.17.</hi> and the Elementes in the Sacramentes for our taſte, ſight, feeling, &amp;c. and yet our ſoules to be nouriſhed not with any or all of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:183865:65"/> theſe outward thinges (for how can outward and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible things nouriſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and immortall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce?) but onely with the ſpirituall graces offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs therein; &amp; this alſo to be wrought in vs (though our Sauiour be in Heauen in reſpect of his body; and wee heere as Pilgrimes and Strangers on the Earth) by the wonderfull &amp; vnſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able working of his holy Spirite in vs, and by the meanes of a liuely and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Fayth: both which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knit togeather, doe ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ioyne togeather things, that be as farre aſunder, in reſpect of diſtaunce of place, as one ende of the earth is from the other; and as farre aſunder, as heauen
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:183865:65"/> and earth them ſelues are: or elſe how could we either beleeue the holy Catholike Church, and feele the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saintes, ſeeing it commonly falleth out, that the members of that holy fellowſhippe, are ſundered one of them from an other, in reſpect of great diſtance of place? or be aſſured that Chriſtes righteouſneſſe is become ours, ſeeing he is in heauen, &amp; wee on the earth, if by Fayth we did not take hold of the ſame, and apply it vnto our ſelues? Beſides, if men ſhould imbrace this ſacramentarie opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what were it, but to euert, as the trueth of Chriſtes promiſes; ſo the certaintie and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redneſſe of his word, who in plaine tearmes, calleth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:183865:66"/> this holy Sacrament, <hi>His bodie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 The ſecond extreami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is, that of conſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſome affirming, that there is deliuered to the people, and they receiue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with the ſubſtance of Bread, the yery ſubſtance of Chriſtes very naturall body; ſo that there is (as it were) an intermingling of both the ſubſtaunces in the action of the Supper. This opinion is iuſtly to be diſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and reproued, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe of the abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which it hath common, with the hereſie of tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation; whereof wee will ſpeake in the next place: but alſo, becauſe it is quite and cleane contrarie to common ſenſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:183865:66"/> confounding and ium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling togeather, two ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and diſtinct ſubſtances and making the leſſe; to witt, the ſubſtance of bread, to comprehende the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is, Chriſts humaine body; yea, euen his verie Godhead: which heauen and earth is not able to containe.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, it doth vtterly take away an eſſentiall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of Chriſtes body: for if Chriſt, in reſpect of his humanitie, be like vnto vs in all thinges, ſinne onely excepted; and we know by the light of reaſon and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that God hath beſtowed vpon vs; yea, by verie experience, that our bodies are circumſcriptible and tyed to a place: it muſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:183865:67"/> needs follow, that Chriſt in reſpect of his Manhood; or Chriſt, as he is Man, is and muſt be tyed to a place, and not be in euery place; as he muſt be, if theſe mens aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be true; which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els indeed, but vtterly to deſtroy Chriſtes body: which I proue againſt them thus. Whoſoeuer taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the eſſentiall propertie of any thing, taketh away the thing it ſelfe: this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is prooued by this Maxime in Logike: If the definition of a thing, which chiefly conſiſteth of the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall propertie of euerie thing be taken away, then the thing defined it ſelfe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo falleth: As for example; If a reaſonable liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is the definition
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:183865:67"/> of a man, be taken away, what ſhall become of man, or where ſhall he appeare, which is the thing defined? But theſe men take away the eſſentiall propertie of a thing, to witte, of a body, which is to be circumſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible or tyed to a place; which is indeed an eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all propertie of the body of man, and therefore of Chriſtes body, as he is man. If any will denie this, it may eaſily be prooued, both by the definition of a body, which is a quantitie, that may be deuided, according to the threefold meaſuring, receiued amongſt men, that is, length, breadth, &amp; thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and alſo by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a place, which is defined to be a nighneſſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:183865:68"/> or touching, of the thing containing, and the thing conteined. The concluſion therefore is, that in taking away place from the body of Chriſt; which they doe, whileſt they place it in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie place, whereas in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thereof, it can be but in one place at one time; they doe vtterly deſtroy the body or humanitie of Chriſt; or at the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found it ſo with the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, as <hi>Eutyches</hi> did, that they make a confuſion (whereas in all trueth and vprightneſſe, there ſhould remaine a diſtinction) of the proprieties of either na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in his bleſſed perſon. But of this ynough in this place, becauſe it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what philoſophicall, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:183865:68"/> becauſe alſo in the next <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ection, we ſhall haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to deale with the like.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The third extreamitie is, that of tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, maintained altogether by the Romiſh Catholikes, which hold that the Bread and Wine, (the ſubſtance thereof vaniſhing away, and nothing being left but the accidentes or qualities thereof, as roundnes, white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, redneſſe, moyſture, &amp;c.) are changed, and that by the power of certaine wordes, ſpoken by the Prieſt (as they cal him) ouer the Elements, they are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the verie naturall body and bloud of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.</p>
                  <p>Concerning this point, and the branches thereof, I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:183865:69"/> will ſpeake particularly and, firſt for the name Tranſubſtantiation, I fear not to affirme, that it is ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie new, and neuer heard of before the dayes of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, who was about the yeare of our Lord 1205. much leſſe was it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed as an article of faith before the Councell of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> a Citie ſo named in <hi>Germanie,</hi> in the dayes of Pope <hi>John</hi> the xxiii. which was about the yeare of our Lord 1415. and therefore by the Popiſh reaſon of reiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing new thinges, eaſily ynough reiected for the noueltie thereof.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 That there is a change I doe not deny; but this is not in reſpect of the nature of the thinges themſelues
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:183865:69"/> but in reſpect of the vſe and ende whereunto they are applyed, becauſe that they are by the Lordes inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſeparated from the common vſe, yea, and from common Bread and Wine, and applyed not onely to a holy vſe, but dedicated alſo to a holy ende, that is, to be ſure ſeales and pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of holy things, to witt, of Chriſts body and bloud, and of the effectes, that by his death and paſſion we receiue. But that this change ſhould be wrought by any wordes, I am ſo farre off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> allowing it as true, that I am verily perſwaded, that it ſauoureth very ſtrongly of a Magicall incantation: and I am ſo much the more confirmed in this, becauſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:183865:70"/> the Papiſtes reioycing as Inchaunters and Sorcerers doe, in their odde numbers: haue added one word; that is <hi>(enim)</hi> to the wordes of inſtitution, ſaying: <hi>Hoe eſt enim corpus meum:</hi> as may appeare in their Miſſall or Maſſe booke.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The groſſe and palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble abſurdities which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this opinion of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, are ſufficient and ſtrong inough of them ſelues, to make it out of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, with al perſons indued with holie wiſedome and vnderſtanding, &amp; to cauſe them to eſteeme of it, not onely as a thing falſe and erronious but very vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and blaſphemous alſo. To reckon vp all, or large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſcourſe vpon the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:183865:70"/> particulars, it is not my purpoſe, but onely to touch ſome ſhortly, yet ſo as the vanitie and falſehood of this great corruption may thereby eaſily appeare.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt I ſay, that this doth vtterly deſtroy the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a Sacrament, which muſt euer conſiſt of two partes; to wit, of viſible ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and inuiſible graces; which can not be, if ſo be it that the nature and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of the elementes, be either chaunged, or vaniſh away, and the things repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the ſame, come in their place; becauſe that the one part of the Sacrament (to witt, the viſible ſigne) is then and there wanting.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, I affirme, that it is iniurious to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:183865:71"/> glorified bodie of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, not onely while it bringeth him from heauen, the place of all bleſſedneſſe, into earth, the place of all miſerie &amp; wretchedneſſe; but alſo whileſt it maketh it to be rent and torne in peeces, not onely with the teeth of good men, (a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which Nature abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth) but with the teeth of the wicked and vngodly; yea with the teeth of Miſe, Dogges, and other vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creatures: yea, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt it maketh it, which is immortall, in immortal glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſubiect to putrifaction, corruption, and Wormes, by reaſon of the long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation thereof, and at the laſt, to conſuming in the fire, (a fact of horrible cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:183865:71"/> if it were Chriſtes fleſh) becauſe it may not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be made away, (as they them ſelues confeſſe) if it be ouertaken with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe, moldineſſe, or any ſuch like.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly I ſay, that by a conſequent it doth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully confound (if not vtterly deſtroy) the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of our Sauiour with his Godhead, whileſt that which is proper and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to his eternall Deitie, to witt, to be euery where, is attributed and aſcribed to his humanitie; which as hath been before ſhewed, and ſhall be more plainely prooued hereafter, is, and muſt of neceſsitie, ſince his aſcenſion, be circumſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible and tied to a place.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:183865:72"/> For otherwiſe, if the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of Chriſtes bodie, haue taken away that propertie of tying to a place, then the like ſhall be perfourmed in all the bodies of the faythfull, becauſe he ſhall change our baſe and vile bodyes, that they may be faſhioned like vnto his glorious body. <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.<hi>21.</hi> But to ſay that our bodyes ſhall be euery where, were a beaſtly and blaſphemous aſſertion; becauſe it ſhould aſcribe that vnto vs, which is proper and peculiar one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God: For vnto him alone it pertaineth, to fill heauen, earth, and all places. Therefore this aſſertion concerning Chriſtes glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied body, muſt of neceſsitie be ſuch likewiſe.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:183865:72"/>
                  <p n="4">4 Fourthly, it doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the Articles of our Fayth, which concerne Chriſtes aſcenſion in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſitting at the right hand of the Father, and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againe, together with all the places of Scripture, that confirme thoſe moſt holy, comfortable, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie poyntes. For if he be heere in reſpect of his bodily power &amp; preſence, how can he be iuſtly ſaid to haue aſcended in reſpect of his bodie, into heauen, and to ſit there at the right hand of his Father, making continuall interceſsion for vs? Or how can it be affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that from thence hee ſhall come with great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and glorie, to iudge the quicke and the dead, ſeeing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:183865:73"/> he is heere on earth already? Let men of the world deeme what they liſt, this is the truth that God hath ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vnto vs in his word, and doe ſteadfaſtly beleeue it in my heart, and will through Gods goodneſſe and ſtrength, alwayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the ſame with my mouth, that from the time of his aſcenſion, the heauens muſt containe Chiſtes na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall bodie, vntill the time that all thinges be reſtored, <hi>Actes 3.21.</hi> that is, euen to the worldes end.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 Fifthly, I ſay that this opinion doth depriue vs of all the ſpirituall graces and comforts, that God the father in his ſonne Chriſt, by ſending the holy Ghoſt the third perſon in the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:183865:73"/> hath beſtowed vpon the whole Church generally, and euery particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereof. For, doeth not our Sauiour Chriſt ſay? <hi>Iohn. 16.7.</hi> I tell you the trueth: It is expedient for you that I goe away; for if I goe not away, that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter will not come vnto you: But if I depart, I will ſende him vnto you. Either this then muſt be true, that we haue the holy Ghoſt by the bodily abſence of our Sauiour Chriſt giuen to the Church, as before is ſayd; or elſe if Chriſt be heere bodily preſent, the holy Ghoſt is not yet come; which you may ſee plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ouerthrowne. <hi>Act. 2.</hi>1.2.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 Sixthly, this aſſertion accuſeth Chriſt of manifeſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:183865:74"/> lying and vntrueth. For he himſelfe hath ſaid, <hi>Math. 26.11.</hi> The poore yee haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with you, but me ye ſhall not haue alwaies. And yet this people dare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that wee haue him continually, not in reſpect of his ſpirituall power and preſence onely, in which reſpect he filleth all places, both in heauen and in earth, and is ſayd to be with the beleeuers euen vnto the end of the world <hi>Matth. 28.20.</hi> But in reſpect of corporall and bodily preſence, then the which nothing can be more abſurde, as hath been before ſhewed.</p>
                  <p>But heere ariſe vp three ſpeciall obiections, to be anſwered: two whereof, are taken for the wordes of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:183865:74"/> the text of holy Scripture, &amp; the third from the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potencie &amp; almightie pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of our Sauiour Chriſt: common thinges indeede, and might as eaſily be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected as obiected: but yet both for the ſtrengthening of them that ſtand, &amp; for the ſatisfying &amp; inſtruction of them that be weake and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt. I will in a word or two, as it were, make a ſhort, yet a ſound, ſufficient, and true anſwere I hope, to euery one of them ſeuerally and by them ſelues.</p>
                  <p>The firſt place obiected, were theſe wordes out of <hi>Iohn. 6.13.</hi> Except yee eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his blood, yee haue no life in you. Wherevnto I anſwere, firſt,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:183865:75"/> that neither theſe wordes, neither the reſt of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, can properly be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode of the Lords ſupper; becauſe that was not at that time inſtituted and ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but rather of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication or partaking with Chriſt, by the meanes of fayth apprehending the worde, and applying parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly vnto our ſelues, all the gracious and ſweete promiſes, that the Lord hath made and offered vnto vs therein: which may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, partly becauſe hee perſiſteth by a a continuall threed of ſpeach as it were, in the metaphor of Bread or Meates, mentioned verſ. 26.27 vſing ſundrie boro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed ſpeaches agreeing well to the circumſtaunce of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:183865:75"/> matter, wherein he was to deale: and partly, becauſe he ſpeaketh ſo often not of eating onely, but alſo of beleeuing; as verſ. 23.40. &amp;c. Which cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly attributed to any outward or materiall thing; as may be gathered, <hi>Rom. 8.24.</hi> Alſo <hi>2. Corinth. 5.7.</hi> But let vs graunt that it were to be vnderſtood of the holy Supper; yet it doth not for all that, eſtabliſh any groſſe and carnall eating of the naturall fleſh or body of our Sauiour Chriſt: for if it were ſo, then had not our Sauiour ſufficiently aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the <hi>Capernaites,</hi> who did groſſely dreame and doate of ſuch a carnal man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation or eating, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had yeelded vnto the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:183865:76"/> ſame. Beſides, if that ſhould be allowed, in what a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſtate ſhould we leaue the holy Fathers; who were long before the time of Chriſtes taking our fleſh vpon him, and therefore could not eate it? And yet our Sauiour affirmeth <hi>Mat. 8.11.</hi> that they were in the kingdome of Heauen: and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>1. Corinth. 10.3.4</hi> that they did all eate the ſame ſpirituall meate that we doe, and did all drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke that we doe; there being no difference at all in reſpect of ſubſtaunce and effect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt their Sacraments and ours, but onely in time, and in outward Elementes: yet in what a miſerable eſtate were Infantes that ſhould
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:183865:76"/> die before they could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate or partake in that holy Sacrament? One of theſe two muſt needes be graunted; either that they muſt haue the Communion miniſtred vnto them; which thing indeed <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did once fantaſtically imagine: but S. <hi>Paul</hi> is flatly againſt it, <hi>1. Corinth. 11.28.</hi> who will haue none admitted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but ſuch as can examine and trie themſelues, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be in the Fayth or no; which Infantes can not doe: or elſe that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, they are all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned alreadie: Both which are verie abſurde and beaſtly. So that you ſee for the auoyding of theſe abſurdities, it can at no hande bee vnderſtoode,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:183865:77"/> either of the Sacramentes, of the groſſe and carnall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Chriſtes body in the ſame, but of the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion or laying hold of him, togeather with the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular application of him to our ſelues by the hand or inſtrument Faith propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ſet foorth vnto vs, by the miniſterie of his Word and Goſpell, or (if you wil for reaſoning ſake) offered vnto vs in the vſe of the Supper, becauſe there is in that reſpect, but one meane giuen vs to take hold of him by; and that is the great grace and gift of Fayth, which we muſt vſe in the Word &amp; Sacraments, as men doe in the oppre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending of Chriſtes righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; which though it
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:183865:77"/> be not eſſentially dwelling in vs, yet it is effectually made ours, whileſt wee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend and lay hold of the ſame by a ſounde and ſure Fayth: And euen in like ſort is Chriſt God &amp; Man togeather with all his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, not onely offered, but laide hold of in the Word and Sacramentes: For of like things, there is alwayes a like conſideration.</p>
                  <p>The ſeconde place, is that ſentence reported by the three Euangeliſtes, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Marke,</hi> and <hi>Luke;</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe alſo, reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the inſtitution of the Supper, which our Sauiour Chriſt vſed, ſaying: This is my body: which they vrge in the letter, after this ſorte: Hath not Chriſt ſaid
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:183865:78"/> it in plaine tearmes? and ſhal I not beleeue it, though that my carnall vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding cannot conceiue the ſame? To all this I anſwere: Firſt, that the queſtion is not of the wordes, for wee as well as they confeſſe the ſame; but of the ſenſe: of which wee will ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none. Secondly, that wee, are bounde to beleeue all ſuch thinges as are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in Gods Worde, though indeed our ſenſuall reaſon, can not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them; yet in ſuch ſort muſt we beleeue the ſame, and to ſuch endes as the Lord himſelfe hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, not yet ſtretching them further, then the Lorde would haue vs; nor reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them to narrow or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:183865:78"/> purpoſes, then the Lord hath appoynted; neither yet fayling in the allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, either in the matter, manner, or end: for if we doe, wee doe nothing elſe thereby but heape vp iuſt condemnation againſt our owne ſoules. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the wordes, and the plainenes of them; I ſay that other words are as plaine as they, both in the old and new teſtament, which muſt yet notwithſtanding, be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe interpreted, then the words themſelues ſeeme to import. For example in the 17 of <hi>Geneſis</hi> 10. Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion is called the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunt betwixt GOD and his people, whereas it was but the ſigne of the Couenaunt: For the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:183865:79"/> it ſelfe was, that hee would be the God of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and in him of all the Faythfull, and of their ſeed after them. So in the new Teſtament, Chriſt ſayth of him ſelfe, <hi>Iohn 15.5.</hi> I am the Vine; whereas wee know and beleeue, that Chriſt was no Vine, but that hee calleth him ſelfe ſo in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine reſemblance; becauſe looke what propertie the fruite of the Vine hath in reſpect of our bodies, to witt, to comfort men, and ro make them glad heartes: the ſame hath Chriſt, and the fruites of his grace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by Fryth, in reſpect af our ſoules: and as the Branches of the Vine haue nothing of them ſelues, but all that they haue, they haue
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:183865:79"/> it from the Vine it ſelfe: ſo none of his members can bring foorth fruite, but by abyding in him; and being made fruitfull through his grace. In like manner is the Bread of the Lords Supper, called his Body, becauſe, as we haue ſayd before, looke what proper and peculiar office the Bread hath or yeeldeth to our naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; the ſelfe ſame doth Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſtes body broken, taken hold of by Faith, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually communicate vnto our ſoules. And this ſpeach is vſuall in the Scriptures, to attribute that to the ſigne, which is proper and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to the thing ſignified, by reaſon of the ſtre ght analogie, proportion, and agreement, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:183865:80"/> the ſigne, and the thing ſignified; and not in any other reſpect, of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, or any other ſuch like fantaſticall dotage.</p>
                  <p>Beſide, the verie circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of time, place, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and manner of doing, doe ſufficiently prooue the vanitie and vntruth of this groſſe interpretation. For this Sacrament being inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by Chriſt him ſelfe a little before his death, in the preſence of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles (who had all their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſatisfied in the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, hearing, and feeling, of the naturall body of our Sauiour Chriſt) he him ſelfe ſitting at the Table with them, and ſpeaking theſe words in their preſence and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:183865:80"/> hearing; it could not bee, that that bread, offered vnto them as the pledge of his body, ſhould be his naturall bodie, or bodie of fleſh, vnleſſe you will ſay, that Chriſt had two bodies: one ſitting at the table, inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the action of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; and an other borne in his handes, and deliuered vnto his Apoſtles: then the which, what can be, not onely more abſurde and blaſphemous, in reſpct of our Sauiour Chriſt him ſelfe; but alſo more vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and vncertaine to vs, as which might prouoke vs to doubt, whether of his bodies were crucified for our tranſgreſsions? Now, as we doe iuſtly reiect this groſſe ſenſe, ſo for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:183865:81"/> of the ignoraunt, and ſtrengthening of the weake, we wil in a few lines put downe the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of theſe wordes. For the better performaunce whereof, I would haue this to be noted.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 In he firſt place, which I am ſure alſo no man of ſounde iudgement can well denie, that all wordes, and therefore theſe of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, muſt be expounded according to the ſubiect, argument, or matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they intreate: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their ſpeaking particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of the Lordes Supper, muſt of neceſsitie be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the Sacrament of the body and blood of our Sauiour Chriſt, exhibited vnto vs in that Supper.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:183865:81"/>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, I would haue this to be remembred, that ſeeing all confeſſr theſe wordes to be ſpoken of the Sacrament, we muſt not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the word Body, is otherwiſe attributed to the Bread, then the nature and qualitie (as it were) of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes will beare; for then if wee ſhould graunt that, wee ſhould eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and ouerthrow all Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes of the Church whatſoeuer; becauſe in this behalfe, or reſpect, there is a like proportion to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in one, as in all: And if one be defaced in reſpect of a wrong ſenſe, the leaſt can hardly, or not at all ſtand vpright.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, that this is the nature of all ſacraments,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:183865:82"/> that the elementes and rites vſed in the ſame, be true and effectuall, not ſignes onely, but teſtimonies and pledges of theſe things, for the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying and ſubiecting of which vnto our ſenſes they were ordained: and yet when I vſe the word, Signe, I would not bee taken as though I meant that they are bare, vaine, or vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Signes, ſuch as Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly vſe to make, but euen thus farre-foorth effectuall, that it is no more true &amp; certaine, that we ſee the ſame with our eyes, touch them with our hands, receiue them with our mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes &amp; eate them; then that is alſo as true and certaine, that the Lord exhibiteth and offereth vnto vs, what
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:183865:82"/> ſo euer they repreſent vnto vs; that is, the verie bodie and bloud of our Sauiour Chriſt. Theſe rules being thus then obſerued, I gather and put downe this true &amp; holie ſenſe of theſe wordes: This is my body: that is to ſay, This Bread which Chriſt tooke, bleſſed, brake; &amp; gaue vnto his Diſciples, and appoynted to be the element of this action, is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentally &amp; ſpiritually, being receiued &amp; eaten by Fayth, a ſure ſigne &amp; an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall pledge, that Chriſts body is become the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all food &amp; nouriſhment of our ſoules. And I vſe theſe words, ſacramentally &amp; ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, that therby I might meete with their groſſe ſlaunder, who when they
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:183865:83"/> heare of a ſigne, and a thing ſignified, ſay that wee doe euacuate and make of no force the Lordes Supper. No, we are ſo farre off from holding any ſuch conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that we know and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that the beleeuers, doe beſide the outward ſignes and elements, truely receiue by the meane of fayth, after a ſpirituall ſort, that which is repreſented by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward elementes; to witte, whole Chriſt, with all his giftes and graces. And yet we doe not imagine, either tranſubſtantiation, or any ſuch like deuiſe; but onely thinke vpon and beleeue, the ſacramentall coniuction of the ſigne and the thing ſignified, For thoſe thinges can not ſtand with the truth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:183865:83"/> of Chriſtes humanitie; as hath been bef re ſhewed: neither indeed are they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for ſaluation. For, that we may be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of Chriſt, it is not of neceſsitie required, that his Body ſhould be really pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vpon the earth; but it rather behooueth vs, by the power of the holy Ghoſt, &amp; through Fayth, to mount vp into Heauen, and there to lay hold of him, that we may ſit with him in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly places, which in this life can not be performed in any other ſort, then in a ſpirituall maner, &amp; through fayth: which fayth is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and confirmed in vs by the holy Ghoſt; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto hee vſeth as inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, the preaching of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:183865:84"/> Gods word, and the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration and vſe of the Sacramentes, by which all our ſenſes are eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it were prouoked &amp; pearſed, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to poſſeſſe Chriſt him ſelfe. So that you ſee, I doe figuratiuely expound theſe wordes, and not groſſely; wherevnto I am drawne partly by theſe three gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Rules heretofore put downe, and partly by the verie dealings of the <hi>Papiſtes</hi> themſelues; who doe not, neither in the Wine of the Supper, the other part of this Sacrament: neither in Baptiſme, the other Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church (which two alone God hath giuen vnto it) acknowledge any ſuch groſſe tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or change; and yet I am
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:183865:84"/> ſure, there is as great reaſon why that alteration ſhould be as well in the Water of Baptiſme, &amp; in the Wine of the Supper, as in the Bread thereof: If there be not, let them ſhew any cauſe, to the contrary if they can.</p>
                  <p>There reſteth now the third obiection, take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the omnipotencie or almightie power of our ſauiour Chriſt preſſed after this manner. Is not Chriſt God, and ſo by that meanes omnipotent? And can not hee performe the trueth of that hee hath ſpoken? To this I anſwere; that though we ſhold grant it as true, that Chriſt, as he is God, can doe all thinges, and be euery where: yet we know that as he is Man, he can not, and therefore the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:183865:85"/> queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betweene the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiators &amp; vs, being now not of the preſence of Chriſtes deitie in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but of the preſence of his humaine body, wee ſay, that if wee ſhould graunt this, yet could it no whit at all preiudice vs; neither could they gaine their cauſe thereby: for vnleſſe they can prooue Chriſt as hee is Man, to be omnipotent, and euerie where (which thing they ſhall neuer bee able to doe) they haue ſayd as much as if they had ſayd nothing.</p>
                  <p>But let vs for reaſoning ſake graunt, that Chriſt as hee is Man, were omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, euen as God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is; doth it therefore follow, that becauſe he can
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:183865:85"/> doe euerie thing, hee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either will do the ſame, or indeed doth it? I ſuppoſe no. For beſides, that in Scholes it is commonly ſaid, <hi>à poſſe ad eſſe,</hi> the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence or reaſon is not good, which were ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent aunſwere to this friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and vaine obiection. Beſides this I ſay, wee that are truely taught of God; doe know, that though we beleeue that the Lord can doe what ſo euer pleaſeth him both in heauen and in earth; which ſerueth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully to magnifie his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie power, and greatly to ſtrengthen our weake fayth; yet we beleeue firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he will not onely doe nothing, but that hee can not doe any thing in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:183865:86"/> of vs, contrarie to that will of his, that he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed for vs in his word. And the reaſon of this is not the abridgement or ſhortning of his power (for be it farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mortall men, to preſume in any thing, though neuer ſo little, to reſtraine the eternall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the immortal God) but becauſe his will and power in reſpect of vs, be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned and knit togeather that looke whatſoeuer he will do, that he can do; and looke whatſoeuer hee can doe, that he will doe. To make this plaine by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. We all know, that God in reſpect both of his ſelfe, and that all thinges are poſsible with him, can if he would, ſaue all men: and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:183865:86"/> yet we feare not to ſay, that in reſpect of vs he can not ſaue all men, becauſe wee know by his reuealed will, that hee will not ſaue them all: For ſome muſt be the veſſelles ordeined for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as well as others, veſſels of ſaluation and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life. The like may we ſay for this matter of the Supper; that though wee were perſwaded, that Chriſt as he is man, might be euery where; yet becauſe he hath reuealed in his Word, that he will haue his bodie to be circumſcriptible and tyed to a place, to witt, Heauen; yea, which is more; to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine place in Heauen, that therefore it can be no iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie at all to him, neither any debaſing of his omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:183865:87"/> power, to ſay that now he cannot be bodily in the Sacrament, much leſſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily in ſo many ſacraments, as be celebrated and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, in ſo ſundry and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite places at one time. And this I thinke ſufficient to all theſe Obiections, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing heere, to finiſh this preſent ſhort Treatiſe, ſauing that I haue thought good in this place, to adde (euen as a challenge to the aduerſe partie, and as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of neceſſary inſtruction, to ſuch as alreadie ſee the trueth) theſe three poyntes following.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 FIrſt, that I am readie in all holy loue, further to aunſwere any thing, that Chriſtianly ſhall be further
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:183865:87"/> obiected concerning this Queſtion: I ſay Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obiected; for if any ſhall either curiouſly or capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly propound any thing, I thinke it moſt conuenient, rather to leaue ſuch in their owne folly, for a ſeaſon, till it pleaſe God at ſome one time or other, euen extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily as it were, to make them to ſee the ſame, if it ſhall ſo pleaſe him, then to ſpend time, and to trauaile in ſatisfying of their vaine curioſitie.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, that though this point of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation brought in by <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes,</hi> be great and groſſe, concerning the matter of the Supper, yet that they faile not alone herein, in that behalfe, but hold many
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:183865:88"/> mo errours concerning that point, ſome of them as pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, if not more groſſe and blaſphemous then this, and ſome of them leſſe: A few I will rehearſe, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring others to conſider of the reſt.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt, in that they make it a ſacrifice Propitiatorie for the quicke and the dead, vtterly euacuating by that meanes, and making of no force, the eternall Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of our Sauiour Chriſt, which conſiſteth in this, that he hath once for all, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Alter of the Croſſe, offered vp himſelfe vnto God the Father, a full and ſufficient Sacrifice, for the ſinnes of the people, as the Apoſtle plainely prooueth in the 7.8.9. and 10. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:183865:88"/> of his Epiſtle to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes:</hi> But no maruell, that they ſhould annihilate his Offices, which deſtroy his perſon; as theſe men doe, by confounding the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties of either nature, as hath been before decreed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, there is but a little leſſe Leuen in that matter, that they holde of <hi>Concountancie,</hi> by which they haue ſpoyled the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the vſe of the Cuppe; which both by Chriſtes owne inſtitution, and by his expreſſe Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſaying; Drinke yee all of this; doth in all trueth and vprightneſſe belong vnto them: and all this they haue done vnder this ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, that becauſe no body is without blood, and they
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:183865:89"/> haue before (preſuppoſing, that the Bread is turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Bodie; as indeede if men will preſuppoſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnpoſsible or vntrue things, euery thing will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of it) eaten the bodie, therefore muſt it needes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that they haue drunke alſo his blood. But I know not, whether I ſhold blame them for their beaſtlineſſe, or reprooue them for their pride, that dare thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuouſly alter the Lordes very Ordinaunce and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, their Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is as corrupt and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, while they make men to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit groſſe &amp; palpable Idolatrie, in falling downe before a peece of Bread: (what doe I ſay? I know
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:183865:89"/> not whether I may call it by that name or no, for it may be diſputed of whether their Maſſe-cake be Bread) and worſhipping a Wafer-cake, the worke of mens hands. But ſuppoſe it were Chriſtes body as they ſay; yet I affirme that they may not adore Chriſtes body a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, yea, and that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not worſhip the ſame of it ſelfe, without horrible ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, becauſe it is a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For though it be true, that Chriſt as he is God, is to be worſhipped as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yea, and Chriſt God and Man in one perſon is to be adored, yet we cannot without great ſinne, and grieuous offence againſt God and his word, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the humanitie or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:183865:90"/> of our Sauiour Chriſt onely.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 To ſpeake of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, circumgeſtation, or carrying of it about, with many other odde toyes of their owne inuention, and largely to lay out the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences thereof, would require ſome proper and fit diſcourſe for that purpoſe; but I will reſerue it till ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, making haſte now, to that which ſhalbe, as the laſt, ſo in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not the leaſt profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of this Treatie: And that is, how a man ſhould draw neere vnto ſuch reuerent myſteries, wherein ſuch excellent gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are offered vnto him, and how he may beſt come to reape and receiue fruite
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:183865:90"/> and comfort by the ſame. All that a man is to deale in, concerning this laſt point, may be well reduced into three ſhort heades or Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt, what he is to doe before communicating or receiuing of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and this I will call in one terme, Preparation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, what hee is to doe or thinke vpon in the time, and at the very inſtant of receiuing: and this I will name, Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, what he is to doe after the time of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: and this I will call, Action or Practiſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Preparation, which is the firſt, reſpecteth either God or man: Now, that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:183865:91"/> which concerneth God, is comprehended vnder true Fayth, and vnfeigned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce, as that which concerneth man, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed vnder ſounde loue. And I call them ſound true, and vnfeigned, and yet not perfect, becauſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection properly ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that, vnto which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be added, cannot be founde in man during this life. And this I ſpeake, partly to ſtop the mouthes of ſuch as dreame of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in this life; and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to teach vs that our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections ſhould not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs from drawing nigh thereto, (ſo that we doe not foſter and foode our ſelues in them,) ſeeing that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Sacrament ſhould
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:183865:91"/> ſtand vs in ſtead, if we were not vnperfect; for it is a helpe and ſuccour ordeined by God, againſt our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall infirmitie and weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. By Fayth, I meane not onely a generall beliefe, of all the Canonicall books of the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; or a grounded know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge alone of the poyntes and principles of Chriſtian religion, but an aſſured per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, that whatſoeuer the Lord hath reuealed in his Word, as hee hath done the ſame for others, ſo he hath done it particularly for mee. So that this Fayth is neceſſarie to him that ſhall communicate, both becauſe that otherwiſe hee being on the earth, cannot take hold of Chriſt in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:183865:92"/> for faith is it by which he may apply vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe particularly Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus and all his merites, to the aſſured feeling of the free pardone and full forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all his ſinnes of the one ſide, and the imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſtes righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on the other ſide, and alſo that thereby he may be aſſured, that that which hee doeth, either in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration or participation of that holy action, is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table before God: for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fayth, it is impoſsible to pleaſe him. Which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties indeed, or effectes rather, if a man onely haue them, ſhall make his Fayth to differ from all the vaine imaginations of Diuels and wicked men whatſoeuer.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:183865:92"/>
                  <p>By Repentance, I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a ſyncere hatred of all our former ſinnes and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities whatſoeuer, and a ſound loue of all righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and well doing, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and louing feare of the maieſtie of God in our heartes: which holy affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doth euery day by little and little worke in vs, the forſaking of our ſelues, and the ſubduing of the ſinfull luſtes and affections of our owne fleſh, to the end, that wee may wholly reſigne our ſelues, to be guided and gouerned by the ſpirit of God, in the ſyncere ſeruice, &amp; worſhip of his Maieſtie. So that hee which feeleth himſelfe truely and vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly ſorrowfull for his
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:183865:93"/> former iniquities, not onely loathing his ſinnes, but euen himſelfe for his ſinnes ſake, and caryeth with him this holy purpoſe, neuer through Gods aſsiſtaunce, to commit the ſame, or any ſuch like: may not onely be aſſured of his vnfeined re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce, and ſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent of the forgiueneſſe of his ſinnes, but alſo with boldneſſe, &amp; yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding with reuerence in reſpect of God, and with humbleneſſe of minde, in reſpect of himſelfe, draw neere to the partaking of theſe holy myſteries.</p>
                  <p>By Loue, which is the thing that concerneth men, I doe not onely vnderſtand the vnfeigned pardoning and forgiuing of others,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:183865:93"/> that haue any maner of way treſpaſſed againſt vs, which is a ſure ſeale and earneſt pennie as it were, that our ſinnes are forgiuen vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God: but alſo ſound reconciliation, after offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces committed, one of vs towardes another, which is a certaine pledge, that our prayers, and all other good thinges that come from vs, are in Chriſtes obedience accepted before God: yea, I meane further by Loue, which is an inward affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the heart, the ſincere and outwarde teſtifying of the ſame, by wordes, deeds, countenaunces, and other meanes, as the Lord ſhall giue occaſion, and our abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie will ſerue to expreſſe the ſame, and that not to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:183865:94"/> our friendes onely, or to our enimies alſo, which is ſomewhat more; but gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to all men, though to ſome in greater meaſure; as to the Houſehold of fayth, our Wiues, Children, and Parentes, &amp;c. and to ſome in leſſe meaſure, as to thoſe that be yet without and be ſomwhat further off by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and kindred.</p>
                  <p>Meditation, which is the ſecond thing, and is to be vſed ſpecially in the time of the celebration of the Lords Supper, conſiſteth chiefely in theſe poyntes: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the outward elements, and the rites vſed in the ſame, as the breaking of the Bread, &amp;c. by which is ſet foorth vnto our ſoules, the crucifying of Chriſts body,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:183865:94"/> the ſhedding of his bloud, &amp;c. and all for our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee muſt not ſtay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but muſt by Fayth riſe vp to Heauen as it were, we are deeply to conſider what great graces the Lord offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto vs in that holy and ſpirituall Banquet; which in my minde may be brought into theſe few pointes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 God ſetteth before the eyes of our Faith in that holy action, firſt, Chriſtes death and paſsion, togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the benefites and effectes which wee reape thereby; and namely, the remiſſion and forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, the full and ſpirituall nouriſhment, that
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:183865:95"/> thorow Chriſt wee haue, both in the outward and inwarde man, euen to the hope of eternall life.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, the myſticall vnion, that is betwixt Chriſt and his Church, hee dwelling in our heartes by faith, and we thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made members of his bodie, of his fleſh, and of his bones.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Fourthly and laſtly, the holy vnitie and agreement, that is &amp; ought to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued amongſt all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his Church, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, or whereſoeuer they be.</p>
                  <p>The third and laſt thing, which I call Action, and is to be performed after the receiuing of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, conſiſteth,</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:183865:95"/>
                  <p n="1">1 Firſt, in earneſt Prayer vnto God not onely for the liuely feeling of theſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces exhibited, but alſo for the fructifying of the word of God and his Sacraments in our heartes; and that not for the time preſent alone, but euen for the whole raſe and courſe of our life.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, in humble thankes-giuing, for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable riches and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of grace and of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which it pleaſeth him in his Church, and namely by the vſe of his Worde and Sacramentes, not onely to offer, but alſo to beſtow vpon his people, the particulars whereof, are before recited. And hereunto wee may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:183865:96"/> by conſideration of this, that the Lord freely and of his owne goodneſſe, giueth vs thoſe merites, not onely when we had not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the leaſt of them, but euen then when euerie one of vs, had deſerued eternall death and condemnation to be powred foorth vpon vs and ours.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 And laſtly, in care and conſcience of a holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, that ſeeing Chriſt dwelleth in our heartes by fayth, and we haue our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life and beeing from him, that therefore wee ſhould ſo liue, as wee may not onely glorifie him in this life, but that when the dayes of our weariſome pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage ſhall be ended, we may be glorified with him
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:183865:96"/> in eternall bleſſedneſſe: which thing, the Lord graunt vs, euen for his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Chriſtes ſake: to whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and one eternall God, be giuen all honour, prayſe, power, and glorie, both of vs, and of all people, euen now and at all times, for euer and euer. So be it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayers">
                  <pb facs="tcp:183865:97"/>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:183865:97"/>
                     <head>A Prayer to be ſaid before a man repaire to the parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Lords Supper.</head>
                     <p>O Eternall GOD and moſt mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I thy poore &amp; vnworthy ſeruant, doe muſt humbly beſeech thee, in Ieſus Chriſt thy deare Sonnes name, and for his ſake, gratiouſly in his death and obedience, to pardone and forgiue mee all my ſinnes what ſo euer, which at any time, or by any manner of meane, I
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:183865:98"/> haue committed againſt thy Maieſtie, or any other. Seale vp in my heart, O Lord, this great benefite of the free pardon and full for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of all my ſinnes, by the aſſured teſtimonie of thy bleſſed ſpirit, bearing record vnto my ſpirit, that I am thy Child, &amp; by vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned pardoning &amp; forgiuing of others, which any maner of way haue offended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee. Make the death &amp; reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy Sonne ſo effectuall in mee, that I may not onely feele and finde in the ſame, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of my ſinnes, and the hope of eternall ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but that I may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed thereby all the dayes of my life, more and more to die vnto ſinne, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:183865:98"/> daily more and more to liue vnto righteouſnes of life &amp; holie conuerſation. And for as much as through thy goodneſſe I haue purpoſed this day, to communicate in the vſe of thy Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, I beſeech thee good Father, to prepare my heart, and to open the eares of my vnderſtanding, that I may not onely reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and profitably hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to thy voyce, ſpeaking vnto mee out of thy word, labouring all the dayes of my life, to conforme my ſelfe in practiſe to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience thereof; but alſo, that I may fruitfully bee partaker of the fruites and effectes of the death and paſsion of thy deare Sonne, which it pleaſed thee in this
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:183865:99"/> Sacrament to offer vnto me. To this end and purpoſe, I beſeech thee to graunt, that I be not carried away in the contemplation and conſideration of the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and corruptible thinges obiected therein to my ſenſes, but that my Fayth may be ſet vp and raiſed, to the beholding and aſſured feeling of thoſe Graces, which it pleaſeth thee by the ſame, to offer vnto mee. Giue me grace, good Lord, to bring with me a ſteadfaſt Fayth in the trueth of thy promiſes, that by it as by an eye, I may behold, &amp; by the ſame, as by a hand, I may apprehend Ieſus Chriſt thy Sonne, ſitting at thy right hand, to be my onely and continuall iuſtifier, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:183865:99"/> and redeemer. Graunt me grace alſo, to bring with me, as an earneſt, hatred of all my former euilles what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer; ſo a ſyncere loue of all righteouſneſſe and wel-doing, that I by the power of thy ſpirite, crucifying the Old man with the luſtes and concupiſcences therof, ſpecially ſuch as beare the greateſt ſway in mee, may be ſtrengthened in the new man; dayly to thinke, ſpeake, &amp; doe thoſe things, which may be acceptable and well pleaſing in thy godly preſence. And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee further, to giue me grace to bring with me, ſound and ſyncere loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes all, yea, euen to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes mine enimies, that I may not onely forget and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:183865:100"/> forgiue all the iniuries and wronges that they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, ſayd, or done, againſt mee: but alſo pray earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto thy Maieſtie for them, and purchaſe and procure their welfare and good, by all the meanes I can. Graunt, O deare Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that I being purged from the filth of ſinne, may be made a fitte receptacle and dwelling place for thee and thy Sonne, to come and dwell in; ſo that ſpending my dayes in reuerence of thy Maieſtie, in the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting of my breathren, and procuring mine own good, I may finiſh my courſe in thy fayth, and ſo be made partaker of eternall glorie, through Ieſus Chriſt thy Sonne, my Lord and onely Sauiour. So be it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:183865:100"/>
                     <head>A prayer to be priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſed, after the publike exerciſes of the Church; as the preaching of the word, &amp; the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lordes Supper ſhall be ended.</head>
                     <p>I Doe vnfaignedly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe (good Father) that the graces are very great, yea, moſt excellent, which thou haſt vouchſafed this day to beſtowe vppon mee, wretched ſinner that I am, by the vſe and parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of thy holy Word and Sacramentes: and namely for that it hath pleaſed thee thereby to increaſe my knowledge, to confirme my Fayth, to aſſure me that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt thy deare Sonne,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:183865:101"/> hath not onely died for me, but alſo giuen him ſelfe to be my ſpirituall nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to eternall life and ſaluation, with innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſuch other benefites and bleſsinges: For theſe, and whatſoeuer other mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, which thy Maieſtie hath freely beſtowed vpon me, I doe yeelde thee the humbleſt thankes and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt prayſe, that poſsibly I can; beſeeching thee to accept mee, and this my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of prayſe &amp; thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, according to the meaſure, that thou merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully haſt beſtowed vpon me. And becauſe I feele my ſelfe, thorough the curſed corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mine owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, woonderfully inclined to the forgetfulneſſe of thy
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:183865:101"/> goodneſſe, I beſeech thee to graue theſe thinges in my heart with a claw of Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, and to imprint them there, that by the ſight thereof, and meditation therein, I may bee prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, daily more and more to magnifie the multitude of thy mercies, which doeſt not onely beſtow vpon me, theſe great and wonderfull graces; but euen then, when by the meanes of my ſinnes, I had deſerued eternall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, haſt gratiouſly giuen mee the ſame. And I pray thee further, to giue me grace (good Lord) to expreſſe this my thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towardes thee, not in wordes onely, but alſo in the deedes of a holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, that I daily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:183865:102"/> and growing in a ſound Fayth, which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by loue, and bringeth foorth all good workes, may order and direct my whole life, to the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy glorie, the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of my breathren, and mine owne eternall comfort at the laſt, through Ieſus Chriſt thy Sonne, my Lord and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sauiour. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:183865:102"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
